<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>Investopedia FAQs</title>
        <description>The 10 most recent frequently asked questions by visitors to Investopedia.</description>
        <link>http://www.investopedia.com</link>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2013 17:25:45</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>FeedCreator 1.7.2</generator>
        <image>
            <url>http://i.investopedia.com/inv/logos/inv88x31.gif</url>
            <title>Investopedia FAQs</title>
            <link>http://www.investopedia.com</link>
            <width>88</width>
            <height>31</height>
        </image>
        <language>en-US</language>
        <copyright>Copyright 1999-2013, Investopedia.com</copyright>
        <ttl>10</ttl>
        <item>
            <title>How do I list the beneficiaries of my life insurance policies if I have a trust? </title>
            <link>http://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/08/revocable-living-trust.asp?partner=rss_faq</link>
            <description>Because most states protect life insurance policies from creditors, most buyer questions come from the confusion created with ownership and beneficiary designations because of tax treatment. This is a rather complicated issue when it comes to life insurance proceeds, because there are two tax issues that raise their head: U.S.</description>
            <guid>http://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/08/revocable-living-trust.asp</guid>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2013 18:10:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Does the federal government fund any NGOs? Which ones?</title>
            <link>http://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/13/federal-government-fund-ngos.asp?partner=rss_faq</link>
            <description>A non-governmental organization (NGO) is a non-profit, citizen-based group that functions independently of government. NGOs are organized on local, national and international levels to serve specific social or political purposes. Despite their independence from government, many NGOs receive significant funding from government entities.While an NGO can be funded entirely or in part by government funding, it may keep its non-governmental status by prohibiting government representatives from membership.</description>
            <guid>http://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/13/federal-government-fund-ngos.asp</guid>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2013 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>If I want to have some cash in a liquid account for unexpected emergencies, what is best? A ...</title>
            <link>http://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/13/what-is-the-best-liquid-account.asp?partner=rss_faq</link>
            <description>It's always a good idea to keep some money set aside in a liquid form, but it's a double-edged sword, because the more liquid your money, the less it's earning. If you never have an emergency, then you can miss out on the chance for substantial earnings by keeping that money in a simple savings account.</description>
            <guid>http://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/13/what-is-the-best-liquid-account.asp</guid>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2013 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>What is a triple tax-free municipal bond?

</title>
            <link>http://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/13/triple-tax-free-municipal-bond.asp?partner=rss_faq</link>
            <description>At its core, a triple tax-free municipal bond is just like any corporate bond: it is a debt instrument, a loan given to a government authority or municipality in order to help it meet certain financial objectives or complete projects in the community.</description>
            <guid>http://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/13/triple-tax-free-municipal-bond.asp</guid>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2013 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>What is the difference between redemption of shares and repurchase of shares?</title>
            <link>http://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/13/difference-between-redemption-and-repurchase-of-shares.asp?partner=rss_faq</link>
            <description>Sometimes, shares of stock offered by a company are not regular, market-driven common shares. Instead, they may be preferred shares, which are considered fixed income securities and are issued with a par value. When that par value is paid back to the purchaser of the preferred share, this is considered a redemption.</description>
            <guid>http://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/13/difference-between-redemption-and-repurchase-of-shares.asp</guid>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2013 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>How do NGOs get funding?</title>
            <link>http://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/13/ngos-get-funding.asp?partner=rss_faq</link>
            <description>A non-governmental organization (NGO) is a non-profit, citizen-based group that functions independently of government. NGOs are organized on local, national and international levels to serve specific social or political purposes.
As non-profit organizations, NGOs rely on a variety of sources for funding projects, operations, salaries and other overhead costs.</description>
            <guid>http://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/13/ngos-get-funding.asp</guid>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2013 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>How are capital gains and dividends taxed differently? </title>
            <link>http://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/12/how-are-capital-gains-dividends-taxed-differently.asp?partner=rss_faq</link>
            <description>The U.S. tax code gives similar treatment to dividends and capital gains, although this will change slightly in 2013. 
Currently, ordinary dividends and short-term capital gains those on assets held less than a year are subject to one's income tax rate.</description>
            <guid>http://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/12/how-are-capital-gains-dividends-taxed-differently.asp</guid>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2013 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>What is pay-as-you-drive auto insurance?</title>
            <link>http://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/12/what-is-pay-as-you-drive-auto-insurance.asp?partner=rss_faq</link>
            <description>To an extent, auto insurance rates are specifically developed based on individual user information. The criteria traditionally considered when determining auto insurance rates include the driver's accident history, type of car they drive, state, age, gender and marital status.</description>
            <guid>http://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/12/what-is-pay-as-you-drive-auto-insurance.asp</guid>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2013 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Are 401(k) loans taxed?</title>
            <link>http://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/12/are-401k-loans-taxed.asp?partner=rss_faq</link>
            <description>Generally, any money you borrow from a 401(k) account is tax exempt. This feature is one of the reasons that - for critical short-term needs - such loans may be a better alternative to hardship withdrawals or high-interest forms of credit. 
As long as you pay the loan back in a timely matter, the only tax consequence comes from the interest some plans require you pay (though the term &quot;interest&quot; is a bit misleading, as the funds go back into the participant's own account).</description>
            <guid>http://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/12/are-401k-loans-taxed.asp</guid>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2013 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Is a dividend reduction a signal to sell?</title>
            <link>http://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/13/dividend-reduction-signal-to-sell.asp?partner=rss_faq</link>
            <description>Although a dividend reduction is generally viewed as a signal to sell, the decision is not as clear-cut as if the dividend were to be eliminated altogether, which would be an unequivocal sell signal. Every manager and board member is aware of the adverse market reaction that is inevitably triggered by news of a dividend cut.</description>
            <guid>http://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/13/dividend-reduction-signal-to-sell.asp</guid>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2013 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
