<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" media="screen" href="/~d/styles/rss2full.xsl"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" media="screen" href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~d/styles/itemcontent.css"?><rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:feedburner="http://rssnamespace.org/feedburner/ext/1.0" version="2.0">

<channel>
	<title>TaxVox</title>
	
	<link>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org</link>
	<description>The Tax Policy Center blog</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2013 17:31:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.org/?v=3.6.1</generator>
		<atom10:link xmlns:atom10="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed" /><feedburner:info uri="taxpolicycenter/blogfeed" /><atom10:link xmlns:atom10="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" rel="hub" href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" /><feedburner:emailServiceId>taxpolicycenter/blogfeed</feedburner:emailServiceId><feedburner:feedburnerHostname>http://feedburner.google.com</feedburner:feedburnerHostname><item>
		<title>One Modest Path to a No-Drama Budget Deal</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/Li1pMeA4ta0/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/17/one-modest-path-to-a-no-drama-budget-deal/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2013 17:31:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Howard Gleckman</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deficit reduction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Federal Budget & Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2014 budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Congress]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Debt Limit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deficit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[government default]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government shutdown]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Policy Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax revenues]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5383</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The conventional wisdom is that next January, Congress and President Obama will be in exactly the same place they’ve been for most of the past three weeks—deep in government shutdown mode. The argument: The recent fiscal battles that ended with last night’s short-term deal to reopen the government and reauthorize Treasury borrowing  buys time but [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The conventional wisdom is that next January, Congress and President Obama will be in exactly the same place they’ve been for most of the past three weeks—deep in government shutdown mode. The argument: The recent fiscal battles that ended with last night’s short-term deal to reopen the government and reauthorize Treasury borrowing  buys time but does nothing to change Washington’s toxic culture.</p>
<p>It is hard to disagree, but there is another possible outcome. No, it isn’t the grand bargain. That’s off the table at least until 2015 and perhaps longer. But Congress and Obama could reach a mini-bargain that would at least take the edge off the current ugliness.</p>
<p>It would be simple and the first steps could be taken in a week or two (although they won’t be).  The deal would look come in three parts.</p>
<p>To start, remember that yesterday’s agreement called for House and Senate negotiators to sit down and finish the 2014 budget process that came to a grinding halt last March. So lawmakers have a ready-made venue for a deal. But what could a realistic agreement look like?  Here is one possibility:</p>
<p>First, Congress would agree to retain the 2013 sequester spending level of $986 billion for 2014 discretionary programs. This is about $20 billion more than the scheduled $967 billion sequester level for 2014.</p>
<p>Second, budget negotiators would allocate this funding level to the appropriations committees. The committees would then write 2014 spending bills that fit within those levels, work out differences between the House and Senate versions, and pass a real budget.  No more mindless across-the-board spending cuts.</p>
<p>Third, Congress would make up the $20 billion of extra agency spending with cuts in mandatory programs such as Medicare and farm subsidies. Of course, lawmakers could always cut a bit more from discretionary or a bit less from mandatory. The numbers are not as important as the process.</p>
<p>A deal such as this would not require deep cuts in any single program. As it happens, Congress is in the midst of rewriting the farm law so it has an easy vehicle to chip away at those programs.  Congressional Republicans and the president have proposed similar Medicare changes such as increases in premiums for high-income retirees and for some Medicare Supplement insurance.</p>
<p>These changes in entitlement spending could all be made without touching the toxic issue of how to adjust Social Security benefits for inflation (aka chained CPI). And there would be no need to battle over the equally toxic issues of revenues.</p>
<p>The framework for this idea is hardly original. It is, in effect, the budget process that’s been in place in one form or another for four decades. And it could be easily completed by mid-January.</p>
<p>Congress abandoned that process in 2010, however. Since then, without any mechanism to settle differences, lawmakers ended up playing a nasty, ad hoc game of threats-and-deadlines that culminated in the madness of the past several weeks.</p>
<p>My proposal is exceedingly modest. It won’t do very much to address the long-term deficit, although well-designed entitlement reductions would build over time. But there is nothing wrong with small confidence-building steps, especially after what Congress and Obama have just gone through.</p>
<p>Given the fiscal chasm between the <a href="http://www.cbpp.org/files/3-19-13bud2.pdf">House and Senate budgets</a>, a big deal in three months is far beyond reach.  The House would cut spending by $5 trillion over 10 years, the Senate by $1 trillion. The Senate would raise taxes by $1 trillion, the <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/numbers/displayatab.cfm?Simid=470">House not at all</a>.</p>
<p>Closing those gaps in today’s environment is impossible. But policymakers might actually get to yes on a mini-deal.  They should at least try.</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=Li1pMeA4ta0:xloe2xP9Be0:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=Li1pMeA4ta0:xloe2xP9Be0:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=Li1pMeA4ta0:xloe2xP9Be0:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=Li1pMeA4ta0:xloe2xP9Be0:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/Li1pMeA4ta0" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/17/one-modest-path-to-a-no-drama-budget-deal/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/17/one-modest-path-to-a-no-drama-budget-deal/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>The Un-Default: Congress Has Become A Seinfeld Episode</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/Zyp-wl9gSGQ/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/16/the-non-default-congress-has-become-an-episode-of-seinfeld/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2013 20:42:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Howard Gleckman</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deficit reduction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Federal Budget & Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2014 budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[default]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deficit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government shutdown]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Seinfeld]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5377</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Like Seinfeld, the classic 1990s TV comedy, Congress is increasingly about…nothing. If the agreement reached by Senate leaders this afternoon sticks (and given recent history, even that is uncertain) Congress has just shuttered much of the federal government for more than two weeks and risked a market-shattering federal default in order to convene a meeting [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Like Seinfeld, the classic 1990s TV comedy, Congress is increasingly about…nothing.</p>
<p>If the agreement reached by Senate leaders this afternoon sticks (and given recent history, even that is uncertain) Congress has just shuttered much of the federal government for more than two weeks and risked a market-shattering federal default in order to convene a meeting of budget negotiators.</p>
<p>According to published reports, that is pretty much the sum total of what lawmakers agreed to today. They will reopen the government until Jan. 15 and give the Treasury renewed authority to borrow money until Feb. 7. This will give Congress and President Obama another three months of artificial fiscal crisis, generate more breathless headlines, and almost certainly drive Washington’s standing with the public even closer to rock bottom.</p>
<p>As a result of this frantic last-minute deal, it is a virtual certainty that we will be in exactly the same place in mid-January as we are today, only colder.</p>
<p>Between now and then, we will return to the status quo ante. The GOP’s Quixotic and self-destructive efforts to demolish the Affordable Care Act have come to naught. The law is not defunded. The individual mandate is not delayed. Even the tax on medical device makers remains.</p>
<p>The GOP did win one concession: The government must do its utmost to prevent low-income people from lying about their income in order to get health insurance.  Otherwise, the 2010 health law goes on unchanged.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Democrats will have three months to relitigate the across-the-board spending cuts known as the sequester.  They conceded at the very beginning of the most recent contretemps that they’d accept ongoing government funding at current sequester levels for the duration of any new spending bill.</p>
<p>Given how matters turned out, they probably regret that quick capitulation. But fear not, they’ll have the opportunity to fight another day. It is in fact why Democrats, not Republicans, ended up insisting on a short-term spending bill as part of today’s agreement</p>
<p>The next turn of the budget screw is scheduled for Jan. 15 when lower 2014 spending levels are due to bite under the next round of the sequester. Today’s deal opens the door for a new fight over  those numbers.</p>
<p>Democrats will demand the next round of cuts be trimmed for domestic spending programs. Some Republicans will ask the same for military spending. Others will fight to maintain the cuts.</p>
<p>The hard-earned fiscal deal hammered out today calls for all this to get worked out—or not—in a budget conference.</p>
<p>Keep in mind the budget conferences used to be a routine part of Congress’ fiscal process. This conference should have begun last March—seven months ago&#8211; after the House and Senate passed their own versions of the 2014 fiscal blueprint.</p>
<p>But the panel never met. For months, Senate Democrats insisted on talks but House Republicans refused to even appoint negotiators. Then, just before the Oct 1 government shutdown, Republicans demanded a budget conference but Senate Democrats refused.</p>
<p>Now, the budget deal says…They should meet.</p>
<p>Lawmakers would instruct the negotiators to produce a  10-year tax and spending blueprint by Dec. 13. But they won’t require such a deal, and certainly won’t set any enforceable parameters for any agreement. Today’s plan simply says they should meet and report something.</p>
<p>All this uncertainty and bitterness. All this lost credibility. All to schedule a meeting.</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=Zyp-wl9gSGQ:r86Zz8yt-Go:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=Zyp-wl9gSGQ:r86Zz8yt-Go:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=Zyp-wl9gSGQ:r86Zz8yt-Go:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=Zyp-wl9gSGQ:r86Zz8yt-Go:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/Zyp-wl9gSGQ" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/16/the-non-default-congress-has-become-an-episode-of-seinfeld/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/16/the-non-default-congress-has-become-an-episode-of-seinfeld/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>The U.S.May Not Default on Friday But Washington Is Still Playing A Dangerous Game</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/ggqpE6tlHcc/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/15/the-u-s-may-not-default-on-friday-but-washington-is-still-playing-a-dangerous-game/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2013 20:46:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Howard Gleckman</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deficit reduction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Federal Budget & Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2014 budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bipartisan Policy Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CBO]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Congress]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[default]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Donald Marron]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government shutdown]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jack Lew]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Policy Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Urban Institute]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5373</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[What’s going to happen on October 18 if Congress doesn’t vote to increase the debt limit? Probably nothing. Make no mistake, Washington is still wading in exceedingly treacherous waters as the President and Congress wrestle over a deal to avoid&#8211;at least for now—a breach of the nation’s borrowing authority. The government risks financial calamity if [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What’s going to happen on October 18 if Congress doesn’t vote to increase the debt limit? Probably nothing.</p>
<p>Make no mistake, Washington is still wading in exceedingly treacherous waters as the President and Congress wrestle over a deal to avoid&#8211;at least for now—a breach of the nation’s borrowing authority. The government risks financial calamity if it fails to pay its bills on time&#8211;which it inevitably will do without the ability to borrow more money. But default may not happen on Thursday, or even this week.</p>
<p>In a recent  <a href="http://branch.com/b/experts-weigh-in-the-debt-ceiling-2">on-line discussion</a> sponsored by the Urban Institute, policy experts from across the ideological spectrum agreed: If necessary, the Administration will probably find ways to put off financial catastrophe for at least an extra few days.</p>
<p>Oct. 18 was never really a drop-dead date in the way that Oct. 1 was the government shutdown deadline. Congress had to pass a spending bill by Oct. 1 to prevent federal agencies from furloughing workers and cease some operations.</p>
<p>By contrast, Oct. 18 found its way into the public debate after Treasury Secretary Jack Lew warned Congress that he expected to have only about $30 billion in cash available by then. After that, he said he could not promise to make all scheduled government payments.</p>
<p>The government may be about out of borrowing authority. But that doesn’t mean it will immediately be unable to pay its bills. As a result, the exact date of actual default remains uncertain.</p>
<p>Government raises money by borrowing and by collecting taxes and other revenues. Even after its borrowing authority is exhausted, it will continue to collect taxes. It may also have some limited additional flexibility to shift money among accounts, although this is uncertain.</p>
<p>As a result, the White House may have a few days or even a couple of weeks to play with.</p>
<p>When exactly will the federal Treasury turn into a pumpkin? The budget experts at the Congressional Budget Office and the Bipartisan Policy Center <a href="http://bipartisanpolicy.org/blog/2013/10/08/bpc%E2%80%99s-x-date-window-narrows-economic-risks-grow">figure</a> the Treasury will run out of money between Oct. 22 and Nov. 1.</p>
<p>Why the range? It turns out the green eyeshade folks can identify projected daily spending quite precisely. They know, for instance, that Social Security must pay $12 billion in benefits on October 23 and that Treasury owes $6 billion in interest on the public debt on October 31. They also know the government must pay out more than $55 billion on Nov. 1.</p>
<p>They are less adept at projecting day-to-day revenues, which can vary quite a lot. That’s why Lew conservatively estimated that he’d be down to his last $30 billion in cash-on-hand by Thursday.</p>
<p>Thus, the drop-dead date may not be Oct. 18. But it will be very soon—and almost certainly before those big payments are due on Nov. 1.</p>
<p>This may create a serious credibility problem for President Obama. If Congress does not act in time, his critics will note with some glee that the sun still rose on Friday morning and Treasury still paid its bills. So, they’ll ask, what’s the rush?</p>
<p>To start, it is impossible to know how financial markets will react in coming days. Which turn of the Washington screw will set them into a panic? Who knows?</p>
<p>We also run the risk that Congress and the White House will miscalculate in their game of chicken and throw the nation into default. That puts us in largely unchartered waters, though my Tax Policy Center colleague Donald Marron noted in <a href="http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/04/actually-the-united-states-has-defaulted/">a recent blog post</a> that an accidental short-term default in 1979 caused a sharp spike in interest rates.</p>
<p>The nation may not go over the fiscal cliff at 12:01 AM on Oct. 18, but in the absence of a fiscal deal in the next day or so, we will be teetering on the edge of the precipice. And that is a dangerous place to be.</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=ggqpE6tlHcc:F0uonrl9iv8:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=ggqpE6tlHcc:F0uonrl9iv8:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=ggqpE6tlHcc:F0uonrl9iv8:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=ggqpE6tlHcc:F0uonrl9iv8:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/ggqpE6tlHcc" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/15/the-u-s-may-not-default-on-friday-but-washington-is-still-playing-a-dangerous-game/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/15/the-u-s-may-not-default-on-friday-but-washington-is-still-playing-a-dangerous-game/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>States Recovering Unevenly and Fed Shutdown Not Helping</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/ZOC5pvE192E/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/15/states-recovering-unevenly-and-fed-shutdown-not-helping/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2013 18:29:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Norton Francis</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[About TaxVox]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5369</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The latest edition of the Tax Policy Center’s State and Local Finance Initiative’s State Economic Monitor finds that revenue growth is accelerating in most states but many jurisdictions faced strong economic headwinds going into the recent partial government shutdown and potential default. In several states, a decline in public sector jobs was boosting unemployment even [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The latest edition of the Tax Policy Center’s <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/stateandlocal/">State and Local Finance Initiative</a>’s <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/stateandlocal/data/State-Economic-Monitor.cfm">State Economic Monitor</a> finds that revenue growth is accelerating in most states but many jurisdictions faced strong economic headwinds going into the recent partial government shutdown and potential default. In several states, a decline in public sector jobs was boosting unemployment even before the partial shutdown.</p>
<p>The State Economic Monitor shows state-by-state economic and finance trends and our <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/stateandlocal/data/data-and-maps.cfm">new page</a> on the website includes interactive maps and charts.</p>
<p>Between August 2012 and August 2013, the public sector shed 94,000 jobs, mostly federal positions. Forty-six states lost federal government jobs. Total government jobs (including state and local positions) increased in 18 states but every state except West Virginia remains below its peak level of government employment, seasonally adjusted.</p>
<p>The trends in unemployment rates vary widely. Thirty-six states have lower unemployment rates than a year ago while twelve states have higher rates.</p>
<p>In Louisiana, for example, the unemployment rate rose from 6.4 percent in August 2012 to 7.0 percent in August 2013, but remained below the 7.3 percent national average. The number of unemployed in the state increased by almost 13,500.</p>
<p>California, Florida, and Nevada had better news:  the unemployment rate in each state fell by 1.5 percentage points or more from a year ago. This is particularly welcome in California and Nevada, where unemployment rates remain substantially above the national average.</p>
<p>Unemployment rates can be difficult to interpret, however, since they depend on how many people enter or drop out of the labor force as well as the sheer number of jobless. For example, Massachusetts, Missouri, and Nebraska added jobs but their unemployment rates rose because more people were looking for work. In Delaware, the number of unemployed was unchanged from a year ago but its unemployment rate increased because 4,000 residents dropped out of the labor force.</p>
<p>Our update does not reflect the partial government shutdown that began on October 1. However, states with high concentrations of federal employees and contractors began to feel the effects almost immediately. The Washington, DC, metro area will be particularly hard hit.  In 2012, federal wages made up about 35 percent of wages in the District of Columbia, 10 percent in Maryland, and 8 percent in Virginia. Tourism in the D.C. area has also likely been more affected than most localities by the shutdown of museums, monuments, and parks.</p>
<p>Along with the Monitor, we’ve updated the <a href="http://slfdqs.taxpolicycenter.org/">State and Local Finance-Data Query System</a>, a tool to download and customize annual state and local revenue and expenditure data. The system is particularly helpful now while these numbers aren’t available on an inactive Census of Governments website. Give it a try.</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=ZOC5pvE192E:RORcopKVYYw:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=ZOC5pvE192E:RORcopKVYYw:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=ZOC5pvE192E:RORcopKVYYw:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=ZOC5pvE192E:RORcopKVYYw:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/ZOC5pvE192E" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/15/states-recovering-unevenly-and-fed-shutdown-not-helping/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/15/states-recovering-unevenly-and-fed-shutdown-not-helping/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Should We Eliminate the Extraordinary Measures?</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/qsLVmJwspzI/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/11/should-we-eliminate-the-extraordinary-measures/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2013 11:37:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Donald Marron</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Federal Budget & Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Debt]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Debt Limit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Extraordinary Measures]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5366</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[You’ve probably heard that Treasury will hit the debt limit on October 17 and soon thereafter it won’t be able to pay all of America’s bills. That second part is true: Congress needs to act soon—preferably before the 17th—so Treasury doesn’t miss any payments. But the first part isn’t: Treasury actually hit the debt limit [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>You’ve probably heard that Treasury will hit the debt limit on October 17 and soon thereafter it won’t be able to pay all of America’s bills. That second part is true: Congress needs to act soon—preferably before the 17<sup>th</sup>—so Treasury doesn’t miss any payments. But the first part isn’t: Treasury actually hit the debt limit way back on May 19.</p>
<p>So how did Treasury keep paying our bills? Extraordinary measures.</p>
<p>When money gets tight, Treasury uses several accounting gimmicks and cash flow sleights of hand—the extraordinary measures—for extra financing. The easiest to explain involves the G-Fund, which is offered to federal employees through their equivalent of a 401(k) plan. As its name implies, that fund invests in government bonds. But the Treasury Secretary has a special power: he can replace those bonds with IOUs. I kid you not. One day the G-Fund has Treasury bonds, and the next it has IOUs. Those IOUs don’t count against the debt limit, but they will eventually be repaid with interest once the debt limit gets increased. Employees don’t lose anything, and Treasury gets some extra financing room.</p>
<p>Such budget gimmickry used to inspire outrage. In 1995, pundits accused Treasury Secretary Robert Rubin of violating his fiduciary duty and <a href="http://www.pionline.com/article/19951127/PRINTSUB/511270718">robbing</a> federal employees when he did this. Today, the same action generates nary a peep; stuffing the G-fund with IOUs is standard operating protocol.</p>
<p>So it is with the other extraordinary measures (for a full list, see <a href="http://gao.gov/products/GAO-12-701">here</a>). Once extraordinary, they are now merely ordinary. No one takes the debt limit seriously until the extraordinary measures are running on fumes, as they are today.</p>
<p>That’s what makes a new proposal from House Republicans intriguing. News reports <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/wonkblog/wp/2013/10/10/the-republicans-want-to-take-away-treasurys-extraordinary-measures-wait-what/">indicate</a> that they want to permanently eliminate some extraordinary measures as part of a debt limit deal.</p>
<p>At first glance, you might worry that killing off those measures would undermine the financing buffer Treasury relies on in times of fiscal discord. But here’s the thing: Our leaders already take that buffer for granted. They know the gas gauge is flashing empty, but they don’t pull into the next station. Instead, they ask the fuel engineers at Treasury how much further we can make it. When the engineers say 30 miles, we drive another 29 ½.</p>
<p>Eliminating the extraordinary measures wouldn’t change the unpleasant brinksmanship of the debt limit. It would merely shift the focus from the day extraordinary measures are exhausted to the day we first hit the debt limit. In return, it would increase the transparency of our goofy budget process and would rid us of the embarrassingly casual use of fiscal gimmicks.</p>
<p>That’s a trade worth considering. But the gains must be balanced against some caveats.</p>
<p>First, the extraordinary measures might be providing some fiscal buffer that remains unused, even now. For example, the Bipartisan Policy Center recently <a href="http://bipartisanpolicy.org/blog/2013/10/09/could-x-date-be-delayed-extending-debt-issuance-suspension-period">noted</a> that an aggressive reading of the law <i>might</i> allow the Treasury Secretary to squeeze a bit more money out of one measure, known as the debt issuance suspension period. As BPC explains, that would be a dubious maneuver, but it would be better than default. So perhaps we could be giving up a bit of flexibility.</p>
<p>Second, eliminating the extraordinary measures would reduce the time the next debt limit increase will last. Early this year, Congress raised the debt limit through May 18, but the extraordinary measures got us well into October. Without those measures, a similar increase now, perhaps to November 22, would come with no extra buffer. That’s a plus for transparency, but a minus if you want to avoid the debt limit as long as possible.</p>
<p>Third, for the same reason, eliminating the extraordinary measures would make it easier for Congress to time when the debt limit comes to a head. That could be a plus or a minus depending on your view of congressional intentions.</p>
<p>Finally, our political system might need several months of a blinking “empty” light to get people ready to act. My sense is that most people are now inured to the flashing and don’t even realize we hit the debt limit months ago. But maybe the flashing still serves some purpose.</p>
<p>In short, the idea of eliminating the extraordinary measures is an interesting addition to the debt limit debate. Those measures provide much less flexibility than they used to. As with star ballplayers, there is some logic to retiring extraordinary measures once they’ve become merely ordinary. But the idea requires more tire-kicking to determine how any costs stack up against the benefits of a clearer, less gimmicky budget process.</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=qsLVmJwspzI:TZOFSXi7fB8:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=qsLVmJwspzI:TZOFSXi7fB8:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=qsLVmJwspzI:TZOFSXi7fB8:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=qsLVmJwspzI:TZOFSXi7fB8:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/qsLVmJwspzI" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/11/should-we-eliminate-the-extraordinary-measures/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>5</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/11/should-we-eliminate-the-extraordinary-measures/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Latest House Debt Limit Plan Will Accomplish Nothing</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/Uybsy2KSu5g/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/10/latest-house-debt-limit-plan-will-accomplish-nothing/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2013 19:30:39 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Howard Gleckman</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deficit reduction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Federal Budget & Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2014 budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Congress]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Debt Limit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fiscal policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sequester]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5362</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Washington may be about to do what it does best&#8211;kick the can down the road. House Republicans have tentatively agreed on a plan to extend the debt limit for about six weeks while keeping the government partially shuttered. Their idea: use the shutdown as a stick to get Democrats to negotiate over “pressing problems,” including more [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Washington may be about to do what it does best&#8211;kick the can down the road.</p>
<p>House Republicans have <a href="http://thehill.com/blogs/on-the-money/budget/327727-gop-looking-at-six-week-debt-limit-extension-to-buy-time" target="_blank">tentatively agreed on a plan </a>to extend the debt limit for about six weeks while keeping the government partially shuttered. Their idea: use the shutdown as a stick to get Democrats to negotiate over “pressing problems,” including more reductions in federal spending.</p>
<p>The White House hints that it might agree to a short-term debt limit extension. Like many ideas that win bipartisan support these days (remember the sequester), this one is terrible.</p>
<p>We’ll know more after the GOP leadership meets with President Obama later this afternoon. But the deal would briefly put off what has become an ugly and dangerous confrontation over the nation’s ability to pay its bills. That buys time—something pols love to do—but accomplishes nothing else. Somewhere along the line, Democrats will insist on also reopening the government for the same six weeks and the GOP may, in the end, go along.</p>
<p>But then what? The still-incomplete House GOP idea is accompanied by vague talk about Democrats and Republicans reopening bigger fiscal negotiations. Maybe this would happen through some sort of super committee or by resuming the long-stalled budget process.</p>
<p>Don’t get me wrong. Talking policy is good. But these discussions will accomplish nothing and leave us in pretty much the same place six weeks from now as we are today. Except that we’ll have had six more weeks of uncertainty.</p>
<p>The chances of Congress and the president reaching a grand bargain, or even a mini-bargain, in the next 42 days are vanishingly small. Talks will founder on the same issues that have prevented serious budget progress for years. Democrats will not agree to any changes in Social Security or Medicare unless Republicans agree to new tax revenues. And Republicans won’t discuss tax hikes.</p>
<p>For all the hand-wringing and threats of the past month, nothing has changed that dynamic.</p>
<p>There is a more productive idea floating around the Senate. This one, first suggested by Republican Susan Collins of Maine, has reportedly attracted the interest of Senate Democratic leader Harry Reid (D-NV). It is exceedingly modest but may make sense in the current gridlocked environment.</p>
<p>Under this plan, both sides would agree to a debt limit extension through December, 2014 and to reopen the government through next September. In return, Democrats would agree to fund the government at sequester levels while giving federal agencies flexibility to make sensible cuts. </p>
<p>This will do little to address long-term fiscal concerns. It will continue to squeeze discretionary spending, which is not the problem. It will do nothing to move the ball on tax reform. But it allows most everyone on Capitol Hill and at the White House to declare victory. Most Republicans will say they got more spending cuts. Most Democrats will say they protected Social Security. Obama will say he averted a real fiscal crisis.  </p>
<p>Hardliners on both sides will still hate it. Tea partiers will complain that it makes no new spending cuts beyond those already agreed to and does nothing to roll back the Affordable Care Act. Liberals will complain that it locks in the sequester-level spending reductions. Pro-defense lawmakers will grumble that Pentagon spending levels are dangerously low.</p>
<p>But this plan&#8211;or something very much like it&#8211; is where lawmakers will eventually end up. The question is: Will they get there soon or only after more tiresome chapters of Perils of Pauline?</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=Uybsy2KSu5g:fH4ydy1s464:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=Uybsy2KSu5g:fH4ydy1s464:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=Uybsy2KSu5g:fH4ydy1s464:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=Uybsy2KSu5g:fH4ydy1s464:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/Uybsy2KSu5g" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/10/latest-house-debt-limit-plan-will-accomplish-nothing/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>4</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/10/latest-house-debt-limit-plan-will-accomplish-nothing/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>It is Never Good When the U.S. Treasury Gets Compared to Brazil</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/qcVHseXAneQ/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/08/it-is-never-good-when-the-u-s-treasury-gets-compared-to-brazil/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2013 17:33:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Howard Gleckman</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deficit reduction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Federal Budget & Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2014 budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Brazil]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Carmen Reinhart]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Debt Limit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Donald Marron]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government shutdown]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kenneth Rogoff]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Treasury bonds]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5358</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The other day, I was talking to a guy who closely watches Washington for big foreign investors. Like most of us, his clients are struggling to understand the debate over the fate of the debt limit. He told me about one investor who asked whether it would be considered a default if Treasury made its [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The other day, I was talking to a guy who closely watches Washington for big foreign investors. Like most of us, his clients are struggling to understand the debate over the fate of the debt limit. He told me about one investor who asked whether it would be considered a default if Treasury made its regular interest payments but failed to pay other creditors.</p>
<p>This would not be a big deal, the investor suggested. After all, he noted, Brazil does it all the time.</p>
<p>I don’t know if Brazil does in fact delay paying creditors, but I do know this: It is never a good thing when Brazil and the U.S. Treasury are mentioned in the same sentence.  Carmen Reinhart and Ken Rogoff figure the South American nation has either defaulted or restructured its sovereign debt nine times—most recently in 1986-87.</p>
<p>In some ways, this says everything you need to know about the current fiscal madness on the Potomac. The dollar is the world’s reserve currency mostly because the U.S. has the world’s biggest economy. But it is also because the U.S. is one of the few nations on the planet where investors need not worry about political risk. We don’t do coups. We don’t do massive currency devaluations.  And we do pay our bills.</p>
<p>Sure, there is interest rate risk. There always is. But eliminating one variable from the financial equation—the concern that the U.S. won’t pay its debts because, well, it doesn’t want to—is an important reason why investors see Treasuries as a safe haven. They know they can stash money here when the world economy trembles or even when their own countries make them nervous. And that, in turn, is one reason why U.S. interest rates remain near historic lows even with a rebounding economy and a federal debt of $17 trillion. Despite everything, investors keep buying our bonds because they know we are good for it.</p>
<p>At least, they did.</p>
<p>The last time investors seriously worried about whether domestic U.S. politics might drive a default was probably sometime during the presidency of Andrew Jackson. But now, they may be getting just a whiff of uncertainty. And, make no mistake, when lenders become uncertain, borrowers pay.  </p>
<p>As my colleague Donald Marron <a href="http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/04/actually-the-united-states-has-defaulted/">notes</a>, in 1979 the U.S. did briefly miss payments on Treasury bills—an inadvertent default caused by a debt limit confrontation and a back office glitch. That temporary hiccup kicked short-term Treasury rates up 60 basis points in a day. Not only was it a huge move, but it stuck for months afterwards.      </p>
<p>So far, the markets don’t seem to believe the U.S. will breach the debt limit this time. But there are hints that this rock-solid belief that Treasuries are the world’s safe haven may be showing some cracks. The cost of buying insurance against default (relatively thinly-traded credit default swaps) is rising. So are rates on very short-term Treasuries. And then there is that guy who is reminded of Brazil.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=qcVHseXAneQ:QyCavRXBkRU:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=qcVHseXAneQ:QyCavRXBkRU:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=qcVHseXAneQ:QyCavRXBkRU:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=qcVHseXAneQ:QyCavRXBkRU:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/qcVHseXAneQ" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/08/it-is-never-good-when-the-u-s-treasury-gets-compared-to-brazil/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>9</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/08/it-is-never-good-when-the-u-s-treasury-gets-compared-to-brazil/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Actually, the United States Has Defaulted</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/JYzvSPAPoiI/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/04/actually-the-united-states-has-defaulted/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2013 12:24:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Donald Marron</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Debt]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Debt Limit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Treasury bonds]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5354</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Since the day of Alexander Hamilton, the United States has never defaulted on the federal debt. That’s what we budget-watchers always say. It’s a great talking point. One that helps bolster the argument that default should not be an option in Washington’s latest debt limit showdown. There’s just one teensy problem: it isn’t exactly true. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Since the day of Alexander Hamilton, the United States has never defaulted on the federal debt.</p>
<p>That’s what we budget-watchers always say. It’s a great talking point. One that helps bolster the argument that default should not be an option in Washington’s latest debt limit showdown.</p>
<p>There’s just one teensy problem: it isn’t exactly true. The United States defaulted on some Treasury bills in 1979 (ht: <a href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748704083904576335420994526968.html?mod=WSJ_PersonalFinance_PF2" target="_parent">Jason Zweig</a>). And it paid a steep price for stiffing bondholders.</p>
<p>Terry Zivney and Richard Marcus describe the default in <a href="http://econpapers.repec.org/article/blafinrev/v_3a24_3ay_3a1989_3ai_3a3_3ap_3a475-89.htm" target="_parent">The Financial Review</a> (sorry, I can’t find an ungated version):</p>
<blockquote><p>Investors in T-bills maturing April 26, 1979 were told that the U.S. Treasury could not make its payments on maturing securities to individual investors. The Treasury was also late in redeeming T-bills which become due on May 3 and May 10, 1979. The Treasury blamed this delay on an unprecedented volume of participation by small investors, on failure of Congress to act in a timely fashion on the debt ceiling legislation in April, and on an unanticipated failure of word processing equipment used to prepare check schedules.</p></blockquote>
<p>The United States thus defaulted because Treasury’s back office was on the fritz in the wake of a debt limit showdown.</p>
<p>This default was temporary. Treasury did pay these T-bills after a short delay. But it balked at paying additional interest to cover the period of delay. According to Zivney and Marcus, it required both legal arm twisting and new legislation before Treasury made all investors whole for that additional interest.</p>
<p>The United States thus did default once. It was small. It was unintentional. But it was indeed a default.</p>
<p>And the nation still stands. But that hardly means we should run the experiment again and at larger scale. Zivney and Marcus examined what happened to T-bill interest rates as a result of this small, temporary default. They find a surprisingly large effect. As best they can tell, T-bill interest rates increased about 60 basis points after the first default and remained elevated for at least several months thereafter. A simple way to see that is to look at daily changes in T-bill yields:</p>
<p><a href="http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/1979-treasury-default.jpg"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-5356" alt="1979-treasury-default" src="http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/1979-treasury-default.jpg" width="664" height="502" /></a></p>
<p>T-bill rates spiked upwards four times in the months around the default. In November 1978, Henry “Dr. Doom” Kaufman predicted that interest rates would rise. They did. Turn-of-the-year cash management disrupted rates as 1978 became 1979. And rates spiked and fell in October 1979 when Paul Volcker announced that the Fed would target monetary aggregates rather than interest rates (the “Saturday night special”).</p>
<p>The fourth big move was the day of the first default, when T-bill rates rose almost 0.6 percentage points (i.e., 60 basis points).There’s no indication this increase reversed in the days that followed (the vertical line on the chart is just a marker for the day of default). Indeed, using more sophisticated means, including comparing T-bill rates to interest on commercial paper, the authors conclude that default led to a persistent increase in T-bill rates and, therefore, higher borrowing costs for the federal government.</p>
<p>The financial world has changed dramatically in the intervening decades. T-bill rates hover near zero compared to the 9-10 percent range of the late 1970s; that means a temporary delay in payments would be less costly for creditors. Treasury’s IT systems are, one hopes, more reliable that 1970s vintage word processors. And one should take care not to make too much of a single data point.</p>
<p>But it’s the only data point we have on a U.S. default. Not surprisingly it shows that even small, temporary default is a bad idea. Our leaders shouldn’t come close to risking it.</p>
<p>P.S. Some observers believe the United States also defaulted in 1933 when it abrogated the gold clause. The United States made its payments on time in dollars, but eliminated the option to take payment in gold. For a quick overview of this and related issues, see <a href="http://economix.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/01/04/fearing-another-u-s-debt-default/" target="_parent">this blog post</a> by Catherine Rampell and the associated comments.</p>
<p>P.P.S. This post originally appeared in <a href="http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2011/05/26/the-day-the-united-states-defaulted-on-treasury-bills/">May 2011</a>. This version has been slightly edited.</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=JYzvSPAPoiI:6gmOOBQX46Y:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=JYzvSPAPoiI:6gmOOBQX46Y:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=JYzvSPAPoiI:6gmOOBQX46Y:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=JYzvSPAPoiI:6gmOOBQX46Y:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/JYzvSPAPoiI" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/04/actually-the-united-states-has-defaulted/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>38</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/04/actually-the-united-states-has-defaulted/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Government Shutdowns Threaten To Become The New Normal</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/drS7uo0qWLE/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/03/government-shutdowns-threaten-to-become-the-new-normal/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2013 19:45:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Howard Gleckman</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Federal Budget & Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Affordable Care Act]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Congress]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[debt ceiling]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Debt Limit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government shutdown]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5350</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[President Obama must continue to refuse to negotiate policy while the government is shut down. If he does not hold firm on this principle, these mindless and grossly inefficient closures threaten to become the new normal. Real shutdowns—and not just vague threats of closures&#8211; could well become a standard part of the annual budget process. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Obama must continue to refuse to negotiate policy while the government is shut down. If he does not hold firm on this principle, these mindless and grossly inefficient closures threaten to become the new normal. Real shutdowns—and not just vague threats of closures&#8211; could well become a standard part of the annual budget process.</p>
<p>And it may not end there. If shutdowns become routine, attention-seeking lawmakers (are there any other kind?) will only escalate their threats. Breaching the debt limit then becomes the next target of opportunity. In just two weeks, we may be there as well.   </p>
<p>This is not an argument for retaining the Affordable Care Act or any of its provisions—the issue ostensibly behind the current stalemate. It is an argument for not slipping into ever-more paralyzing fiscal gridlock. In this case, the process matters far more than the immediate policy controversy.</p>
<p>Already much of Washington and Wall Street has become dangerously blasé about the current shutdown. Oh, a few days or a week—no big deal. If it goes longer than that, they insist, then we’ll worry.</p>
<p>This is an exceedingly dangerous view that ignores the reality that every parent learns the hard way: Unchecked bad behavior begets worse behavior.</p>
<p>Just take a look at what’s happened to the Senate in recent years. Once, filibusters were rare exceptions. Now, they are constant. Nearly every bill, no matter how trivial, requires 60 votes for passage in a body that historically required a mere majority.</p>
<p>Similarly, presidential nominations are now routinely blocked for reasons only occasionally having to do with the qualifications of the nominee. Lawmakers have learned that they can take a nominee hostage in order to send an ideological message or convince an administration to change a regulation.</p>
<p>As a result, behavior that was once rare has become as routine as the Senate’s daily prayer.</p>
<p>The same thing has happened with the budget process. Over the past four decades, various efforts to manage the deficit eventually failed in the same way: Each included special rules aimed at waiving their spending limits in the event of an emergency. But lawmakers soon learned they could use these exceptions whenever they wanted. They got addicted, the waivers became the legislative norm, and efforts to control spending withered.</p>
<p>I fear the same is about to happen with government shutdowns. Once those who would use the shutdown as a useful legislative lever succeed, it will become a tool of choice. True, it couldn’t be used in every circumstance, but there would be enough opportunities to make it the next filibuster.</p>
<p>Obama deserves as much blame for this turn of events as the tea party Republicans. It was the president who, in the summer of 2011 willingly used a similar artificial crisis to try to win a <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/publications/url.cfm?ID=1001698" target="_blank">grand fiscal bargain </a>with the congressional GOP. His effort was a miserable failure, but it taught lawmakers that fiscal hostage-taking works.</p>
<p>Late last year, Washington <a href="http://taxpolicycenter.org/publications/url.cfm?ID=412730" target="_blank">repeated the same exercise</a>—again bringing the government to the brink of a shutdown and threatening a breach of the nation’s debt limit.</p>
<p>So it should have been a surprise to no one that headline-seeking lawmakers used a similar set of circumstances to once again manipulate the political system to their advantage. But this time, the mere threat of a shutdown wasn’t enough. This time, they had to go the next step and padlock the doors (some of them, anyway).</p>
<p>If the president cracks under the pressure, lawmakers of both parties will learn a simple lesson: You get what you want by forcing a government shutdown. It will happen again and again. And most of us will come to regret it.</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=drS7uo0qWLE:q0PeOztKjHs:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=drS7uo0qWLE:q0PeOztKjHs:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=drS7uo0qWLE:q0PeOztKjHs:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=drS7uo0qWLE:q0PeOztKjHs:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/drS7uo0qWLE" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/03/government-shutdowns-threaten-to-become-the-new-normal/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>6</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/03/government-shutdowns-threaten-to-become-the-new-normal/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>It’s Groundhog Day Over the Debt Ceiling</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/nzjgtSXReDE/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/02/its-groundhog-day-over-the-debt-ceiling/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2013 15:06:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>William Gale</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deficit reduction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Federal Budget & Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[debt ceiling]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Debt Limit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deficit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[national debt]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spending]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5347</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[If you recently heard the news that Congress is debating the merits of raising the debt ceiling, don&#8217;t think you have time-traveled back to 2011 or to 2012. In the absence of Congressional action, and barring some extraordinary measures, the debt ceiling is set to be breached sometime in the next several weeks, and the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you recently heard the news that Congress is debating the merits of raising the debt ceiling, don&#8217;t think you have time-traveled back to 2011 or to 2012. In the absence of Congressional action, and barring some extraordinary measures, the debt ceiling is set to be breached sometime in the next several weeks, and the U.S. stands to gain nothing by not raising it.</p>
<p>The debt limit &#8220;debate&#8221; is not about limiting the size of government, entitlement reforms, or tax reform. The proof of that is that there are no major items like that on the table right now.</p>
<p>Instead, Republicans in Congress are yet again debating whether Congress should authorize the government to pay for spending—wait for it—that Congress has already authorized the government to undertake! Yes, it really is that silly of a situation.</p>
<p>It is also cowardly—if the Republicans don&#8217;t want the spending to occur, they should specify the spending cuts, not put the United States in a literally impossible position by saying &#8220;you must spend this amount of money, but you are not authorized to finance that spending via taxes or borrowing.&#8221; When other countries authorize spending, they typically proceed by implicitly authorizing the increase in borrowing needed to fund such spending. Of the advanced economies, only Denmark has a mechanism like our debt ceiling, and it has never been used as a negotiating tactic for spending cuts.</p>
<p>While it is difficult to predict the precise magnitude and composition of the economic effects of hitting the debt ceiling, it is clear that the effects will not be good ones. At the broadest level, creating a politically manufactured crisis that threatens the full faith and credit standing of government debt hardly seems like a smart or patriotic thing to do. In recent testimony to Congress, my Tax Policy Center colleague <a href="http://www.urban.org/UploadedPDF/904601-The-Costs-of-Debt-Limit-Brinksmanship.pdf">Donald Marron</a> (of the Urban Institute) noted that not raising the debt ceiling (or even toying around with the idea) could raise interest costs, and create economic uncertainty thus hurting the ailing economy.</p>
<p>The U.S. recently suffered economic costs just by flirting with the idea of not raising the ceiling. The debt ceiling showdown of 2011 has been estimated to have cost taxpayers <a href="http://www.gao.gov/assets/600/592832.pdf">$1.3 billion</a> for that fiscal year and <a href="http://bipartisanpolicy.org/sites/default/files/Debt%20Limit%20Analysis%20Sept%202013.pdf">$18.9 billion</a> over 10 years.</p>
<p>Actually hitting the debt ceiling would result in either a default or reduction in spending. If the U.S. were to default on its debt, even for the short-term, the economy could suffer the negative consequences. As Donald Marron has <a href="http://dmarron.com/2011/05/26/the-day-the-united-states-defaulted-on-treasury-bills/">pointed out</a>, the United States defaulted on some Treasury bills in 1979, and this small technical default caused T-bill interest rates to increase by about 60 basis points and remain elevated for at least several months thereafter. The effect of a sustained debt ceiling breach on interest rates could be significantly larger this time around. And with debt equal to 70 percent of GDP now, the overall effects of interest hikes could be substantial. Moreover, an increase in government rates will raise other interest rates on other lending that is keyed to Treasuries.</p>
<p>Cutting more spending from this weak economy would not be a smart strategy. CBO <a href="http://www.cbo.gov/publication/44445">recently estimated</a> that repealing the sequester could create between 0.3 and 1.6 million jobs in the third quarter of 2014 as well as increase real GDP growth by 0.2-1.2 percent.</p>
<p>The political craven-ness of Republican resistance to raising the debt ceiling can be seen by the fact that, even if the recent Republican House of Representatives budget had been enacted, we would still have had to raise the debt ceiling, if not now, then in short order, because even their budget proposes a significant increase in government debt.</p>
<p>If Republican members of Congress seem to be willing to allow the government to hit the debt ceiling, it may be because Republican voters want them to. A recent <a href="http://articles.washingtonpost.com/2013-09-18/politics/42176322_1_government-funding-bill-debt-ceiling-borrowing-limit">Washington Post &#8211; ABC poll</a> showed that 61 percent of Republicans survey would support &#8220;Congress not raising the debt limit and letting the government default on paying its bills and obligations.&#8221; This held even though 66 percent of the Republicans surveyed agreed that if the government &#8220;cannot borrow more money to fund its operations and pay its debts&#8230; it would cause serious harm to the U.S. economy.&#8221; This is, to put it mildly, an odd set of opinions to hold simultaneously.</p>
<p>While Republican Congressmen and voters seem willing to negotiate over the full faith and credit of the U.S. government, in the end, the debt ceiling should simply be raised to pay for spending that Congress has already authorized and not used as a tactic that could hurt the United States, with no apparent gains.</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=nzjgtSXReDE:zEpWjvNhft8:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=nzjgtSXReDE:zEpWjvNhft8:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=nzjgtSXReDE:zEpWjvNhft8:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=nzjgtSXReDE:zEpWjvNhft8:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/nzjgtSXReDE" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/02/its-groundhog-day-over-the-debt-ceiling/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>4</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/02/its-groundhog-day-over-the-debt-ceiling/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Would the Government be Shuttered if Obamacare were Romneycare?</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/Vj8AvLMLHQk/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/01/would-the-government-be-shuttered-if-obamacare-were-romneycare/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2013 20:02:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Len Burman</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Federal Budget & Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health Care]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Affordable Care Act]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government shutdown]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5343</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Enrollment in the new health care exchanges begins today and the government is partially shut down in protest—never mind that Obamacare funding is largely immune to the shutdown. The Republicans in the House appear to be getting most of the blame for the shutdown because they insist that continued government funding be tied to at [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Enrollment in the new health care exchanges begins today and the government is partially shut down in protest—never mind that Obamacare funding is largely immune to the shutdown.</p>
<p>The Republicans in the House appear to be getting most of the blame for the shutdown because they insist that continued government funding be tied to at least a temporary delay in the implementation of the President’s healthcare law, a nonstarter in the Democratic controlled Senate and the White House.</p>
<p>I wondered how the debate might be different if 2008 had produced a President Romney rather than Obama. Candidate Romney would have campaigned on the <a href="http://www.urban.org/health_policy/Massachusetts-and-Health-Reform.cfm">success of the Massachusetts health reform</a>, arguably his greatest accomplishment as governor. The system of subsidies, mandates, and a regulated health insurance marketplace were the model for the Affordable Care Act.</p>
<p>If we had Romneycare, the White House and Republicans would be trumpeting the remarkable success of the free (but regulated) market in providing a wide range of choices of insurance plans in most markets and pushing prices down. That is what choice and competition do! (And, exactly what<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/09/25/us/politics/officials-detail-premium-costs-of-health-plan.html?_r=0"> seems to be happening </a>now under Obamacare.)</p>
<p>Democrats might complain that many of the affordable health insurance plans <a href="http://www.kaiserhealthnews.org/Daily-Reports/2013/September/26/details-on-health-law-cost-and-coverage.aspx">have high deductibles </a>that could create significant hardships for middle-income families if they get sick. The Republicans would remind us that high deductibles help constrain medical spending by making health insurance consumers cost conscious. (In the alternative reality that is Obamacare, Republicans bemoan the high deductibles and the Democrats mostly remain silent.)</p>
<p>Democrats, chafing under Romneycare would hate the individual mandate and the burden it puts on middle-class workers unlucky enough to work for an employer that doesn’t provide health insurance. Republicans would call it individual responsibility; people should be discouraged from eschewing insurance only to put the burden of paying for their care on others when they get sick. <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/02/15/health/policy/health-care-mandate-was-first-backed-by-conservatives.html">Conservative think tanks</a> would point out that the mandate is the lynchpin of any free market solution.</p>
<p>Republicans might not have included the employer mandate—they are more hesitant to put new burdens on businesses—but Obama suspended the mandate for a year and it’s likely <a href="http://www.urban.org/health_policy/url.cfm?ID=412865">an area where the two parties might find common ground</a> if they were on speaking terms. Unions would howl in protest that, without a mandate, employer-sponsored insurance might go the way of the dodo bird. Republicans would say “good riddance.” Companies should focus on producing better products and services and leave health insurance administration to others.</p>
<p>The surtaxes on those with high incomes probably wouldn’t be in Romneycare. President Bush’s historic expansion of Medicare to cover prescription drugs mostly borrowed to cover the cost.</p>
<p>So a key difference is that Republicans really hate the new taxes. As is often the case, what seems to be a fight about spending is really much about taxes.</p>
<p>But another difference is that absent a landslide victory in Congress, President Romney would have needed a significant number of votes from Democrats to pass health reform since many Republicans don’t believe the federal government should be in the health insurance business. A bipartisan bill would surely have muted Democratic criticism.</p>
<p>The bottom line is that the main problem many Republicans have with the Affordable Care Act is that it is Obamacare rather than Romneycare. (Well, actually, it is Romneycare.) They’re not invested in the law since it passed with only Democratic votes. And they really hate the taxes.</p>
<p><em>Follow me on <a href="http://twitter.com/lenburman">twitter</a>.</em></p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=Vj8AvLMLHQk:KtEyI_sj5SA:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=Vj8AvLMLHQk:KtEyI_sj5SA:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=Vj8AvLMLHQk:KtEyI_sj5SA:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=Vj8AvLMLHQk:KtEyI_sj5SA:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/Vj8AvLMLHQk" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/01/would-the-government-be-shuttered-if-obamacare-were-romneycare/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>14</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/10/01/would-the-government-be-shuttered-if-obamacare-were-romneycare/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Could the GOP Boost Tax Reform By Adding the Idea to the Debt Limit?</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/cZ3r_aKcQs4/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/26/could-the-gop-boost-tax-reform-by-adding-the-idea-to-the-debt-limit/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2013 22:10:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Howard Gleckman</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deficit reduction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Federal Budget & Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Proposals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2014 budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Congress]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Debt Limit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[House GOP]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[National Review]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5339</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[House Republicans reportedly are considering several ways to add a framework for tax reform to legislation needed to increase the federal government’s borrowing authority. Could such a rider increase the chances of reform happening in the near future? Sadly, no. Indeed, it is likely to bury a tax code rewrite even more deeply in Washington’s [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republicans reportedly are considering several ways to add a framework for tax reform to legislation needed to increase the federal government’s borrowing authority. Could such a rider increase the chances of reform happening in the near future? Sadly, no. Indeed, it is likely to bury a tax code rewrite even more deeply in Washington’s partisan muck.</p>
<p>The GOP leadership remains unsure about what this amendment would look like, to say nothing of what they’d finally accept once the bill works its way through the legislative meat grinder. But it seems pretty clear that adding tax reform to their debt limit wish list is little more than a talking point. And real reform would remain as elusive as ever, if not more so.</p>
<p>Keep in mind that the House GOP is not going to include an actual tax reform plan in its version of the debt bill. They are, in fact, far from agreeing among themselves on what such a proposal would look like. But they could try to tie an outline of their tax reform goals, and perhaps a timetable for reform, to a debt limit extension.</p>
<p>The tax reform amendment would likely be one of many ideas the GOP would add to their version of a debt limit extension, which Treasury estimates must be passed no later than Oct. 17. Other possible GOP asks include a delay in the Affordable Care Act, permitting the Keystone pipeline, and rolling back a raft of environmental regulations as well as part of the Dodd-Frank financial reform law. <em>The National Review Online</em> published <a href="http://www.nationalreview.com/corner/359534/revealed-house-gops-debt-ceiling-plan-jonathan-strong?wpisrc=nl_wonk">one version</a> last evening.</p>
<p>When it comes to tax reform, Republicans seem to be looking at a couple of alternatives. The package leaked to <em>National Review</em> would demand congressional approval of a framework akin to the <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/numbers/displayatab.cfm?Simid=435" target="_blank">reform plan </a>offered by House Budget Committee Chair Paul Ryan (R-WI). His proposal contains deep cuts in individual and corporate rates and unspecified curbs in tax preferences.</p>
<p>But would the GOP amendment include anything more than platitudes about rate cuts and loophole closers? That’s hard to say. One thing is certain: If it gets any more specific than that, count on Democrats to rip the GOP for wanting to scale back popular tax preferences such as the deductions for mortgage interest and charitable gifts, and the exclusion for employer-sponsored health insurance.</p>
<p>This would attract attention to the Republican’s interest in tax reform, but not in a good way.</p>
<p>The second piece of their package might be some sort of timetable for a tax code rewrite. The <em>National Review </em>story included some form of undefined “fast-track” authority for reform.</p>
<p>Last spring, some GOP leaders talked about tying progress on tax reform to a series of short-term debt limit extensions. In other words, the debt limit might be increased for, say, three months. Once the Ways &amp; Means Committee reported out a revenue code rewrite, the debt limit would be increased for another three months. When the Finance Committee passed its version, the feds could borrow for another 90 days, and so on.</p>
<p>This is, of course, why including such a wish list on a must-pass debt bill would be so counterproductive. There are Democrats, including Senate Finance Committee Chair Max Baucus (D-MT), who would dearly love to do tax reform. But even the often-independent Baucus won’t buck his caucus by agreeing to a framework for reform with a legislative gun to his head. Especially one that raises no more revenue than the current tax code—a non-starter for the Democratic leadership.</p>
<p>Even some White House aides might like to see a timetable for corporate tax reform. But there is little chance President Obama would swallow anything like what the GOP is cooking.</p>
<p>Last month, I <a href="http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/27/how-washington-will-use-the-coming-budget-wars-to-duck-hard-choices/" target="_blank">wrote </a> that Washington’s never-ending fiscal crises have become a convenient excuse for lawmakers of both parties to avoid making tough budget choices. Instead of cutting entitlement spending or reforming the tax code, they distract their partisans with mud-wrestling with dead-end rhetoric. I fear that this latest tax reform gambit is yet another bit of political sleight of hand masquerading as serious fiscal policy.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=cZ3r_aKcQs4:Bj5wXd2XV3A:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=cZ3r_aKcQs4:Bj5wXd2XV3A:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=cZ3r_aKcQs4:Bj5wXd2XV3A:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=cZ3r_aKcQs4:Bj5wXd2XV3A:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/cZ3r_aKcQs4" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/26/could-the-gop-boost-tax-reform-by-adding-the-idea-to-the-debt-limit/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>5</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/26/could-the-gop-boost-tax-reform-by-adding-the-idea-to-the-debt-limit/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>An Upcoming Debate on Whether Private Equity Should Pay Higher Taxes</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/NtDNi7NYD-I/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/24/an-upcoming-debate-on-whether-private-equity-should-pay-higher-taxes/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2013 20:55:52 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Howard Gleckman</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Carried Interest]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Investment Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Types of Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Akin Gump]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[carried interest]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John C. Hart]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lee Sheppard]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Patrick B. Fenn]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[private equity firms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Simpson Thatcher & Bartlett]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Steve Rosenthal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Steve Shay]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sun Capital]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Analysts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Policy Center]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5336</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[If you are looking for a break from the dreary debate over the budget, our friends at Tax Analysts will be holding a roundtable discussion on Friday afternoon on the tax treatment of private equity firms. The issue has generated lots of interest since the First Circuit Court of Appeals ruled that a private equity [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you are looking for a break from the dreary debate over the budget, our friends at <i>Tax Analysts</i> will be holding a <a href="http://www.taxanalysts.com/www/conferences.nsf/KeyLookup/SCAO-9BEPXK?OpenDocument">roundtable discussion</a> on Friday afternoon on the tax treatment of private equity firms. The issue has generated lots of interest since the First Circuit Court of Appeals ruled that a private equity firm was engaged in a “trade or business” under ERISA, the federal pension law.</p>
<p>If the court’s decision is extended to tax law, these firms and their investors could face significantly higher taxes than they do today. . </p>
<p>My Tax Policy Center colleague Steve Rosenthal <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/publications/url.cfm?ID=904602">has argued</a> the ruling, in a case called <a href="http://media.ca1.uscourts.gov/pdf.opinions/12-2312P-01A.pdf">Sun Capital Partners v. New England Teamsters &amp; Trucking</a>, could result in a private equity fund being treated as an operating business rather than a passive investor. If Steve is right, returns to the firm’s managers could be taxed as ordinary income, rather than at lower capital gains rates. In addition, tax-exempt and foreign investors could be subject to U.S. tax on their returns. Steve has urged Treasury to write regulations to clarify these rules.</p>
<p>Interestingly, while Congress continues to debate whether the compensation of private equity managers, aka carried interest, should be taxed at higher rates, the reasoning in this case could open the door for higher taxes under current law, without the need for new legislation.</p>
<p>A key question:  Do private equity firms such as Sun Capital merely act as investors or do they manage the businesses they acquire in order to boost their profits. The firms make the legal argument that they only invest, but their promotional materials often claim that they aggressively intervene in the management of underperforming  companies before flipping them at a profit.   </p>
<p>Who’s right? <em>Tax Analysts</em> has arranged a roundtable to debate the issue. Besides Steve, participants will include Patrick B. Fenn, a partner at Akin Gump; John C. Hart, a partner at Simpson Thatcher &amp; Bartlett, Harvard Law professor Steve Shay, and <em>Tax Analysts</em> contributing editor Lee Sheppard. <i>Tax Analysts</i> publisher Chris Bergin will moderate.    </p>
<p>The roundtable will be held at the National Press Club in Washington from 3-5 PM. It should be interesting.</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=NtDNi7NYD-I:94vjRTnclZU:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=NtDNi7NYD-I:94vjRTnclZU:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=NtDNi7NYD-I:94vjRTnclZU:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=NtDNi7NYD-I:94vjRTnclZU:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/NtDNi7NYD-I" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/24/an-upcoming-debate-on-whether-private-equity-should-pay-higher-taxes/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/24/an-upcoming-debate-on-whether-private-equity-should-pay-higher-taxes/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Senator Lee’s New Reform Plan Focuses on Young Children</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/UjbOB7cuSRA/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/19/senator-lees-new-reform-plan-focuses-on-young-children/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2013 14:24:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Elaine Maag</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[About TaxVox]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Individual Income Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marriage Penalty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Expenditures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Proposals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Child Tax Benefits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[child tax credit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Elaine Maag]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[family taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[low-income taxpayers]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5332</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[At an AEI panel discussion earlier this week, Senator Mike Lee (R-Utah) unveiled the Family Fairness and Opportunity Tax Reform Act. The centerpiece is an additional $2,500 tax credit for all children under age 17. The plan retains the $1,000 child tax credit under current law. Unlike the current credit, the new credit would not [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>At an <a href="http://www.aei.org/events/2013/09/17/tax-reform-the-family-and-the-pursuit-of-happiness-a-new-plan-by-senator-mike-lee/">AEI panel discussion</a> earlier this week, Senator Mike Lee (R-Utah) unveiled the <a href="http://www.lee.senate.gov/public/index.cfm/blog?ID=8f0918ae-cc8f-48bb-88e2-7a9385894c1a">Family Fairness and Opportunity Tax Reform Act</a>. The centerpiece is an additional $2,500 tax credit for all children under age 17. The plan retains the $1,000 child tax credit under current law. Unlike the current credit, the new credit would not phase out at higher income levels.</p>
<p>Lee’s idea is straightforward—cut taxes for families with children and raise them for households with high itemized deductions.</p>
<p>He’d eliminate the standard deduction and personal exemption (except for dependents under 17) and replace them with a nonrefundable $2,000 per person credit. He’d also repeal the Alternative Minimum Tax and end the taxes associated with the 2010 Affordable Care Act (ACA).</p>
<p>He would also eliminate all but two itemized deductions, including those for state and local taxes. He’d keep the mortgage interest deduction (capped at $300,000 of debt) and the deduction for charitable giving—and make those available to all taxpayers.</p>
<p>The plan would have just two rates, 15 percent on the first $87,850 for single people (twice that for couples) and 35 percent—higher than the 25 percent top rate in other GOP plans.  (The plan would eliminate most <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/briefing-book/key-elements/family/marriage-penalties.cfm">marriage penalties</a> for higher-income households and provide marriage bonuses for many. High-income households with one earner and many children would get a huge tax cut.)</p>
<p>While Lee says he’d like to aim for even lower rates, his current design seems to recognize  that you can’t slash tax rates for all without losing billions (or even trillions) of dollars in tax revenue.  However, the 35 percent rate is significantly lower than the 39.6 percent top rate—plus surtaxes associated with the ACA—that applies to top incomes under current law. We don’t know yet whether the plan is revenue neutral because important details haven&#8217;t been specified.</p>
<p>Lee would remove many households from the federal income tax rolls. But he sees no special reason why the key feature of his plan—the added $2,500 per-child tax credit—needs to be a tax credit. He’d be willing to use a direct spending program instead (something my colleague <a href="http://blog.metrotrends.org/2013/09/end-child-poverty/">Austin Nichols might think was a better idea</a>).</p>
<p>If the new child credit were instead a transfer payment, the plan wouldn’t increase the number of people who don’t pay federal income tax, but it would still provide substantial assistance to families with children, albeit with higher administrative costs. By acknowledging that such a child credit is effectively spending, Lee challenges critics to assess the merits of the plan.</p>
<p>We ought to be talking about whom the federal government should assist and how much aid they ought to get, without turning policy inside out by making every benefit program a tax preference when direct spending might make more sense. I agree with Senator Lee. Spending programs and tax policy can often accomplish the same thing. We should evaluate benefits for families with children and see what form of subsidy makes the most sense. Maybe in the process we could stop obsessing about who does—and does not—pay federal income tax.</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=UjbOB7cuSRA:QK4w5eQLxNw:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=UjbOB7cuSRA:QK4w5eQLxNw:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=UjbOB7cuSRA:QK4w5eQLxNw:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=UjbOB7cuSRA:QK4w5eQLxNw:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/UjbOB7cuSRA" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/19/senator-lees-new-reform-plan-focuses-on-young-children/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/19/senator-lees-new-reform-plan-focuses-on-young-children/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>The Costs of Debt Limit Brinksmanship</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/FUfyOpeFJPA/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/18/the-costs-of-debt-limit-brinksmanship/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2013 18:54:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Donald Marron</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[About TaxVox]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Federal Budget & Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Debt]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Debt Limit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Donald Marron]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[interest rates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[stock market]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Treasury Department]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5326</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Today I had the chance to testify before the Joint Economic Committee about a perennial challenge, the looming debt limit. Here are my opening remarks. You can find my full testimony here. I’d like to make six points about the debt limit today. First, Congress must increase the debt limit. Failure to do so will [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><i>Today I had the chance to testify before the Joint Economic Committee about a perennial challenge, the looming debt limit. Here are my opening remarks. You can find my full testimony <a title="Donald Marron's full testimony" href="http://www.urban.org/publications/904601.html" target="_blank">here</a></i><i>.</i></p>
<p>I’d like to make six points about the debt limit today.</p>
<p><b>First, Congress must increase the debt limit.</b></p>
<p>Failure to do so will result in severe economic harm. Treasury would have to delay billions, then tens of billions, then hundreds of billions of dollars of payments. Through no fault of their own, federal employees, contractors, program beneficiaries, and state and local governments would find themselves suddenly short of expected cash, creating a ripple effect through the economy. A prolonged delay would be a powerful “anti-stimulus” that could easily push our economy back into recession.</p>
<p>In addition, there’s a risk that we might default on the federal debt. I expect that Treasury will do everything it can to make debt-service payments on time, but there is a risk that it won’t succeed. Indeed, we have precedent for this. In 1979, Treasury accidentally defaulted on a small sliver of debt in the wake of a debt limit showdown. That default was narrow in scope, but financial markets reacted badly, and interest rates spiked. If a debt limit impasse forced Treasury to default today, the results would be more severe. Interest rates would spike, credit would tighten, financial institutions would scramble for cash, and savers might desert money market funds. Anyone who remembers the financial crisis should shudder at the prospect of reliving such disruptions.</p>
<p><b>Second, Treasury doesn’t have any “super-extraordinary” measures if the debt limit isn’t raised in time.</b></p>
<p>Pundits have suggested that Treasury might sidestep the debt limit by invoking the 14<sup>th</sup> Amendment, minting extremely large platinum coins, or selling gold and other federal assets. But Administration officials have said that none of those strategies would actually work.</p>
<p><b>Third, debt limit brinksmanship is costly, even if Congress raises the limit at the last minute.</b></p>
<p>As we saw in 2011, brinksmanship increases interest rates and federal borrowing costs. The Bipartisan Policy Center—building on work by the Government Accountability Office—estimates that crisis will cost taxpayers almost $19 billion in extra interest costs.</p>
<p>Brinksmanship also increases uncertainty, reduces confidence, and thus undermines the economy. In 2011, for example, consumer confidence and the stock market both plummeted, while measures of financial risk skyrocketed.</p>
<p>Finally, brinksmanship weakens America’s global image. The United States is the only major nation whose leaders talk openly about self-inflicted default. At the risk of sounding like Vladimir Putin, such exceptionalism is not healthy.</p>
<p><b>Fourth, as this Committee knows well, our economy remains fragile.</b></p>
<p>Now is not the time to hit it with unnecessary shocks.</p>
<p><b>Fifth, as the CBO confirmed yesterday, the long-run budget outlook remains challenging</b>.</p>
<p>Deficits have fallen sharply in the past few years. But current budget policies would still create an unsustainable trajectory of debt in coming decades. Congress should address that problem. But the near-term fiscal priorities are funding the government and increasing the debt limit.</p>
<p><b>Finally, Congress should rethink the debt limit and the entire budget process</b>.</p>
<p>Borrowing decisions cannot be made in a vacuum, separate from other fiscal choices. America borrows today because this and previous Congresses chose to spend more than we take in, sometimes with good reason, sometimes not. If Congress is concerned about debt, it needs to act when it makes those spending and revenue decisions, not months or years later when financial obligations are already in place. When the dust settles on our immediate challenges, Congress should re-examine the entire budget process, seeking ways to make it more effective and less susceptible to dangerous, after-the-fact brinksmanship.</p>
<div>
<hr align="left" size="1" width="33%" />
<div>
<div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=FUfyOpeFJPA:ltdmwQ5NgsI:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=FUfyOpeFJPA:ltdmwQ5NgsI:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=FUfyOpeFJPA:ltdmwQ5NgsI:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=FUfyOpeFJPA:ltdmwQ5NgsI:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/FUfyOpeFJPA" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/18/the-costs-of-debt-limit-brinksmanship/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>4</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/18/the-costs-of-debt-limit-brinksmanship/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Is Obamacare the GOP’s White Whale?</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/H_NTLROUZ18/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/17/is-obamacare-the-gops-white-whale/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2013 18:29:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Howard Gleckman</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deficit reduction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Federal Budget & Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health Care]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2014 budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Affordable Care Act]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Congress]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Debt Limit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Moby Dick]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Republicans]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stan Collender]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5321</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[ “The White Whale swam before him as the monomaniac incarnation of all those malicious agencies which some deep men feel eating in them…All that most maddens and torments; all that stirs up in the lee of things;…all that cracks the sinews and cakes the brain; all evil…visibly personified …and made practically assailable in Moby Dick” [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p> “The White Whale swam before him as the monomaniac incarnation of all those malicious agencies which some deep men feel eating in them…All that most maddens and torments; all that stirs up in the lee of things;…all that cracks the sinews and cakes the brain; all evil…visibly personified …and made practically assailable in Moby Dick”</p></blockquote>
<p><i>Moby Dick or, The White Whale</i> Herman Melville</p>
<blockquote><p>“We&#8217;re going to have a whale of a fight.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>House Speaker John Boehner, Aug 26, 2013 <a href="http://www.idahostatesman.com/2013/08/26/2726580/popkey-boehner-visits-boise-still.html">on the coming fiscal showdown</a>.</p>
<p>No, Speaker Boehner is not Ahab, captain of Melville’s doomed whaling ship Pequod.  But to many in his caucus, Obamacare is the White Whale. It surely is all that most maddens and torments. And like Ahab, many House Republicans and their deep-pocket supporters seem willing to risk their ship and all hands to destroy it.</p>
<p>At least 54 GOP House lawmakers insist they will <a href="http://tomgraves.house.gov/news/documentsingle.aspx?DocumentID=349424" target="_blank">refuse to fund the government </a>past Oct 1 unless the Affordable Care Act is defunded until 2015. Many of them will likely refuse to extend the debt limit (which will be reached in mid-October) unless the health law is defunded. On this ship, it is not the captain but a passionate and mutinous minority of the crew that holds the tiller.</p>
<p>They feel a real urgency since people will begin buying insurance under the ACA in just two weeks. They know it will be very tough to eliminate that coverage once it begins on Jan 1.</p>
<p>That is one reason why Democrats will never agree to defund the health law now. And it is why the very demand risks locking both parties into dangerous and uncompromising positions.  My Urban Institute colleague Donald Marron will <a href="http://www.jec.senate.gov/republicans/public/index.cfm?p=CommitteeNews&amp;ContentRecord_id=c739ff26-d28a-4ce8-944b-1cb98329bd85">testify tomorrow</a> to the Joint Economic Committee on the economic risks of debt limit brinksmanship.    </p>
<p>As long-time Washington budget watcher Stan Collender notes in his <a href="http://www.capitalgainsandgames.com/blog/stan-collender/2763/years-budget-fight-isnt-about-budget">blog</a>, the obsession with Obamacare fundamentally changes the dynamics of Washington’s fall fiscal ritual—which is tiresome but mostly predictable. Usually, the partisans argue over mere dollars. Democrats want to spend more, Republicans want to spend less, and, in the end, they settle on a number in between.</p>
<p>But as long as the House GOP insists on defunding the Affordable Care Act, there can be no middle-ground. Democrats won’t hobble the president’s signature legislative accomplishment just before it begins to benefit millions of uninsured people. Will they give up something else instead—maybe agree to fund federal agencies at somewhat revised sequester levels for another year?</p>
<p>That will be a tough sell. Remember, liberals are feeling a bit frisky themselves these days—having sunk the nomination of Obama favorite Larry Summers as Fed chairman and having helped walk back the president’s vow to attack Syria.</p>
<p>Where does this leave us? Maybe, at the last moment, this cadre of Republicans will finally abandon their Obamacare obsession.  Maybe, at the last moment, Boehner will save the ship by pulling together a coalition of pragmatic Republicans and Democrats. They might agree to some additional modest spending cuts as the price of another year of relative budget peace, but leave the ACA intact. The ensuing mutiny of the committed could cost Boehner his speakership, of course.     </p>
<p>Or maybe this year’s fiscal showdown ends like the Melville classic, with the Pequod sunk with all souls lost save Ishmael, who is left adrift in the vast Pacific, on a coffin.    </p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=H_NTLROUZ18:COQd6Ef7tks:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=H_NTLROUZ18:COQd6Ef7tks:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=H_NTLROUZ18:COQd6Ef7tks:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=H_NTLROUZ18:COQd6Ef7tks:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/H_NTLROUZ18" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/17/is-obamacare-the-gops-white-whale/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>9</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/17/is-obamacare-the-gops-white-whale/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Eight in Ten U.S. Households Pay Social Security and Medicare Taxes</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/A_WmYWbxb8A/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/12/eight-in-ten-u-s-households-pay-social-security-and-medicare-taxes/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2013 20:37:20 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Howard Gleckman</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Individual Income Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medicare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Payroll taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Security]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The US Tax System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Types of Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[payroll tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Policy Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[who pays no tax]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5313</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[While relatively few low-income people pay federal income tax, a large and growing share owe Social Security and Medicare payroll taxes, according to new estimates by the Tax Policy Center. As a result, while about 43 percent of all households will pay no federal income tax this year, only 14 percent will pay neither income [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>While relatively few low-income people pay federal income tax, a large and growing share owe Social Security and Medicare payroll taxes, according to <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/numbers/displayatab.cfm?template=simulation&amp;SimID=479.">new estimates</a> by the Tax Policy Center. As a result, while about <a href="http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/29/and-now-for-the-movie-fewer-americans-pay-no-federal-income-tax/">43 percent</a> of all households will pay no federal income tax this year, only 14 percent will pay neither income nor payroll tax.</p>
<p>Once household income reaches $100,000, just about everyone pays both. But the story is more complex for those at the lower end of the economic food chain. Despite the oversimplified and inaccurate claims of some commentators, most low- and moderate-income households do pay Social Security and Medicare taxes, and the vast majority pay more in payroll tax than in income tax.   </p>
<p><a href="http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/Payroll-Income-Tax-graph-9-12-13.gif"><img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-5317" alt="Payroll-Income Tax graph 9-12-13" src="http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/Payroll-Income-Tax-graph-9-12-13-300x223.gif" width="300" height="223" /></a></p>
<p>Nearly 63 percent of households in the lowest 20 percent of income (those making less than about $23,500) will pay some Medicare and Social Security taxes in 2013.</p>
<p>Many of those who don&#8217;t are the low-income elderly. Because they do not work, they pay no payroll taxes. And because their incomes are so low—often only Social Security benefits—they pay no income tax.</p>
<p>My TPC colleague Amanda Eng estimates that among the elderly in the bottom 20 percent of income just 5 percent will pay payroll taxes and less than 1 percent will pay income tax. By contrast, among households with no members 65 and older, more than 8 in 10 will owe payroll tax while just 6 percent pay income tax.</p>
<p>Among all taxpayers in the middle 20 percent (between about $45,000 and $76,000) more than 85 percent will pay Social Security and Medicare taxes this year while 72 percent will pay federal income tax. Even among middle-income households, more than eight in ten will pay more payroll tax than federal income tax.</p>
<p>TPC also looked at who will pay payroll and income tax in 2023. A decade from now, a significantly larger share of low-income households will pay both levies. Among those in the lowest 20 percent of income, 72 percent will owe payroll taxes, up from 63 percent today. And 20 percent will pay income tax, up from 13 percent today.</p>
<p>Interestingly, while a greater share of middle-income households will owe federal income tax (86 percent v. 72 percent), slightly fewer will be paying payroll tax (82 percent v. 86 percent).</p>
<p>Overall, 80 percent of households will pay Social Security and Medicare taxes while 65 percent will pay income taxes. Two out of every three will pay more payroll tax than income tax. TPC includes the employer share of payroll taxes in its estimates.  </p>
<p>The rising percentage of taxpayers a decade from now will largely be driven by an improving economy that returns to full-employment and the scheduled expiration of the relatively generous versions of the Earned Income Tax Credit and the American Opportunity Tax Credit.    </p>
<p>The message from all this is pretty clear: It is simply not true that more than 40 percent of U.S. households pay no taxes, or even no federal taxes. While many may not pay federal <i>income </i>tax this year, 80 percent will pay Social Security and Medicare taxes. They do indeed, as the phrase goes, have skin in the game.</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=A_WmYWbxb8A:TDcDh-oafic:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=A_WmYWbxb8A:TDcDh-oafic:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=A_WmYWbxb8A:TDcDh-oafic:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=A_WmYWbxb8A:TDcDh-oafic:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/A_WmYWbxb8A" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/12/eight-in-ten-u-s-households-pay-social-security-and-medicare-taxes/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>8</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/12/eight-in-ten-u-s-households-pay-social-security-and-medicare-taxes/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>The Demise of Estate Tax Planning</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/QPYngqC9q6Q/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/10/the-demise-of-estate-tax-planning/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2013 18:13:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Howard Gleckman</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[estate tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The US Tax System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Types of Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Arden Dale]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income tax planning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lawyers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Policy Center]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5309</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[A fascinating story in last Friday’s Wall Street Journal reports what I suppose was an inevitable trend: With the estate tax exemption now up to $5.25 million ($10.5 million for couples) estate tax lawyers are running out of work. So, writes the Journal’s Arden Dale, they are turning to income tax planning for high-net worth clients. The Tax [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A fascinating story in last Friday’s <i>Wall Street Journal</i> <a href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424127887323893004579057443731074838.html?KEYWORDS=estate+planning">reports</a> what I suppose was an inevitable trend: With the estate tax exemption now up to $5.25 million ($10.5 million for couples) estate tax lawyers are running out of work. So, writes the <i>Journal’s</i> Arden Dale, they are turning to income tax planning for high-net worth clients.</p>
<p>The Tax Policy Center <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/UploadedPDF/1001660-TN-estate-taxes-after-ATRA.pdf">estimates</a> that this year only 3,780 estates will have assets exceeding $5 million and barely 2,000 of those will have $10 million or more. Since it is likely that most people with estates of this size have already done their tax planning, there is just not going to be a lot of new business out there.</p>
<p>Of course, some states have lower thresholds that will keep estate tax attorneys busy. And the wealthy have reasons other than than pure tax savings to do estate planning. But still, what’s a lawyer to do? Some are even urging clients to unwind their trusts.</p>
<p>Dale finds that some have turned to another form of tax planning—finding ways for rich clients to shuffle money to relatives with the aim of reducing income tax liability. As Dale notes, this sort of asset shifting is much simpler than the complex world of trusts.</p>
<p>For instance, a high tax-bracket parent could lend money to a lower-bracket child at today’s very low interest rates. The child could invest the funds and live off capital gains, dividends, and interest but the parent would get the inital loan back.  Or, a wealthy client can maximize contributions to retirement plans such as 401(k)s and Roth IRAs since distributions from those accounts are not subject to the new 3.8 percent investment tax that was enacted as part of the 2010 Affordable Care Act.</p>
<p>There is nothing new about wealthy people hiring lawyers to help them reduce their income taxes. For years, they’ve been turning ordinary income into capital gains, deferring income, or shifting income offshore in order to lower their taxes.    </p>
<p>But it is interesting that, as the estate tax exemption has steadily increased (under a Democratic president of all things), estate tax lawyers are scrambling for work. With both income tax rates and estate tax exemptions rising it is hardly surprising that enterprising tax lawyers will follow Willie Sutton’s timeless advice and go where the money is.        </p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=QPYngqC9q6Q:WURGSaBYElI:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=QPYngqC9q6Q:WURGSaBYElI:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=QPYngqC9q6Q:WURGSaBYElI:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=QPYngqC9q6Q:WURGSaBYElI:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/QPYngqC9q6Q" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/10/the-demise-of-estate-tax-planning/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>13</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/10/the-demise-of-estate-tax-planning/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>A Closing Window for Some Same-Sex Couples to File 2012 Tax Returns</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/GMZD9TnEJBo/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/05/a-closing-window-for-some-same-sex-couples-to-file-2012-tax-returns/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2013 20:18:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Roberton Williams</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Individual Income Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marriage Penalty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Same-sex couples]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[filing jointly]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[marriage bonus]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[marriage bonus and penalty calculator]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[marriage penalty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[married filling jointly]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[same-sex couples]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[same-sex marriage]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5306</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Last week’s IRS ruling on same-sex marriages received a lot of attention. Going forward, a same-sex married couple must file federal income tax returns as married, regardless of whether the state where they live recognizes their marriage. In addition, same-sex couples may—but don’t have to—file amended returns for some earlier years to recoup any extra [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Last week’s <a href="http://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-drop/rr-13-17.pdf">IRS ruling</a> on same-sex marriages received a lot of attention. Going forward, a same-sex married couple must file federal income tax returns as married, regardless of whether the state where they live recognizes their marriage. In addition, same-sex couples may—but don’t have to—file amended returns for some earlier years to recoup any extra taxes they paid because they had to file as individuals.</p>
<p>But most reports on the ruling have missed an important detail: the IRS will begin applying the new rule on September 16. That gives same-sex couples who haven’t yet filed their 2012 tax returns just a few more days to file as individuals if they choose to do so. For some, that could mean a much smaller tax bill.</p>
<p>At issue are <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/briefing-book/key-elements/family/marriage-penalties.cfm">marriage penalties</a>, the additional income tax some couples have to pay because they must file their federal tax returns as married. Because tax parameters aren’t proportionately higher for couples than for singles—for example, higher tax brackets for joint filers apply at less than twice the income as for individuals and phase-in and phase-out ranges don’t start at double the income level—some couples pay more income tax than if they were single. That’s most likely to be the case if spouses have similar incomes.</p>
<p>For example, if both spouses earn $100,000, have no children, take the standard deduction, and have no other income, their 2012 tax bill filing jointly would be $38,319. If they could file individual returns, each would pay $18,731 in income tax. The total—$37,462—would be $857 less than what they’d pay as a couple. They pay a marriage penalty.</p>
<p>Of course, many couples pay less tax than they would if they were single and thus get a marriage bonus. If one spouse earned all of the hypothetical couple’s $200,000 income and the other earned nothing, filing jointly would save them nearly $9,000, a hefty marriage bonus.</p>
<p>It’s not always obvious whether a couple will pay more or less tax because they are married. You can get an idea of the difference between filing jointly or as individuals using the <a href="http://taxpolicycenter.org/taxfacts/marriagepenaltycalculator.cfm">Tax Policy Center’s Marriage Bonus and Penalty Calculator</a>. But one warning: the calculator cannot take account of every tax situation—you’ll have to complete and compare joint and single tax returns to find the exact bonus or penalty. Of course, the same rules will soon apply to both same-sex and heterosexual couples.</p>
<p>For a few more days, however, same-sex couples who were legally married last December 31 and who haven’t yet filed their 2012 tax returns can avoid marriage penalties one last time by filing individually. If you’re in that situation, you could save a lot of money if you get your 2012 tax return in soon.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Disclaimer: the Tax Policy Center doesn’t give tax advice.  If you have any doubts about how the new tax laws would affect you, consult a real tax advisor.</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=GMZD9TnEJBo:i9c1nU2fgKM:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=GMZD9TnEJBo:i9c1nU2fgKM:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=GMZD9TnEJBo:i9c1nU2fgKM:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=GMZD9TnEJBo:i9c1nU2fgKM:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/GMZD9TnEJBo" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/05/a-closing-window-for-some-same-sex-couples-to-file-2012-tax-returns/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>10</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/05/a-closing-window-for-some-same-sex-couples-to-file-2012-tax-returns/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>How Do High-Income People Avoid Paying Federal Income Tax?</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/kArCTTOA9YQ/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/05/how-do-high-income-people-avoid-paying-federal-income-tax/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2013 13:26:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Roberton Williams</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Individual Income Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Expenditures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[foreign tax credit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[high-income]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[high-income taxpayers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medical expense deduction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[no tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pay no income tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax expenditures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax preferences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax shelters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax-exempt bonds]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax-exempt interest]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[worldwide tax]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5302</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Most of the 43 percent of Americans who the Tax Policy Center projects will pay no federal income tax this year make very little money. Some are middle-income households that qualify for enough tax preferences to zero out their tax bills. But more than 70,000 households with income over $200,000 will pay no federal income [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Most of the <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/taxtopics/federal-taxes-households.cfm">43 percent of Americans</a> who the Tax Policy Center projects will pay no federal income tax this year make very little money. Some are middle-income households that qualify for enough tax preferences to zero out their tax bills. But more than 70,000 households with income over $200,000 will pay no federal income tax in 2013. How will they do that?</p>
<p>Some have very high medical expenses but the two biggest reasons are linked to their investments: foreign tax credits and tax-exempt bonds.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nM7orhQIzKM&amp;feature=c4-overview&amp;list=UUiODGs5uF-ZdoLTrRXlkv7g"> TPC’s hit video</a> explains why the 43 percent pay no federal income tax. But for a closer look at why high-income households pay no income tax, it helps to turn to the IRS’s Statistics of Income (SOI) division.</p>
<p>Each year, SOI focuses on two overlapping groups of returns with income over $200,000: those who pay no income tax to the U.S. and those who pay no tax worldwide.</p>
<p>The first includes people whose U.S. liability is zeroed out by domestic tax preferences combined with foreign tax credits and the exclusion of overseas income taxed abroad. The second includes only those who don’t pay any net income tax at all. The analysis also uses two alternative measures of income to define high-income tax units: adjusted gross income (AGI) and “expanded income,” which adds excluded income such as tax-exempt interest and untaxed Social Security. (The second measure is closer to—but not the same as—the Tax Policy Center’s “<a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/UploadedPDF/412871-measuring-income.pdf">expanded cash income</a>.”)</p>
<p>The <a href="http://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-soi/13insprbulhignincome.pdf">latest installment of the SOI analysis</a> found that about 3 percent of the 143 million tax returns filed in 2010—4.3 million—had expanded income over $200,000. Almost 33,000 (0.8 percent) paid no tax to the IRS in 2010 and about half of those paid no income taxes worldwide.</p>
<p>Nearly 40 percent of those paying no domestic income tax benefitted most from the foreign tax credit and roughly another third saved most because of tax-exempt interest. Various itemized deductions mattered most for about 15 percent of tax filers.</p>
<p>Among those who had no worldwide tax liability, coupon-clipping was the biggest reason. Fully 60 percent of the 16,000 returns paying no net tax benefited most from tax-exempt bond interest. Extraordinary medical expenses, which are currently deductible to the extent that they exceed 10 percent of AGI, were the main reason why another 11 percent of high-income households paid no tax.</p>
<p>It’s likely that some taxpayers save a lot by using tax avoidance techniques that don’t show up in the SOI data.  Some of the most successful tax shelters simply defer or otherwise mask income so that a well off person can appear to have relatively modest means.</p>
<p>Most of the high-income tax filers who don’t pay income tax hardly get off scot-free. Those who don’t pay the IRS because of foreign tax credits obviously ante up to other countries. Those who benefit from the exclusion of municipal bond interest pay an implicit tax since tax-exempt bonds earn a lower interest rate than taxable bonds. And, of course, high-income households pay many other taxes. But for a small group of lucky duckies, our current system of tax preferences makes it possible to avoid paying any federal income tax.</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=kArCTTOA9YQ:4GjUXE1K6Ac:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=kArCTTOA9YQ:4GjUXE1K6Ac:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=kArCTTOA9YQ:4GjUXE1K6Ac:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=kArCTTOA9YQ:4GjUXE1K6Ac:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/kArCTTOA9YQ" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/05/how-do-high-income-people-avoid-paying-federal-income-tax/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>6</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/05/how-do-high-income-people-avoid-paying-federal-income-tax/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Are Some Americans Paying Federal Income Tax They Don’t Owe?</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/ZA2mrOIb4TQ/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/03/are-some-americans-paying-federal-income-tax-they-dont-owe/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2013 19:02:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Howard Gleckman</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Individual Income Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Compliance]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The US Tax System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Types of Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[federal income tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jacob Mortenson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[James Cilke]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jonathan Zytnick]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Joshua Lawrence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[low-income taxpayers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Michael Udell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[National Tax Association]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[non-filers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[non-payers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Policy Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tiffany Young]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[who pays no income tax]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5296</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Headline got your attention? No, it isn’t a come-on for a new tax avoidance scheme. Rather, it reflects an interesting but little known problem with the federal income tax system: People who have tax withheld from their paychecks but, for some reason, don’t file returns. For many, ignoring their 1040 means they are paying tax they [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Headline got your attention? No, it isn’t a come-on for a new tax avoidance scheme. Rather, it reflects an interesting but little known problem with the federal income tax system: People who have tax withheld from their paychecks but, for some reason, don’t file returns. For many, ignoring their 1040 means they are paying tax they don’t owe.</p>
<p>According to one estimate, in 2003 more than 8 million people had almost $16 billion in taxes withheld but did not file 1040s. Not only did many pay tax they didn’t owe but some likely missed out on refundable credits that could have improved their well-being.  </p>
<p>To some degree, this is the flip side of another set of numbers that get far more attention—those American who pay no federal income tax.  The other day, the <a href="http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/29/and-now-for-the-movie-fewer-americans-pay-no-federal-income-tax/">Tax Policy Center estimated</a> that about 43 percent of Americans will be off the federal income tax rolls in 2013, down from 47 percent in 2009.</p>
<p>Nearly three in four non-payers file 1040s. Nearly all pay some tax—sales taxes, payroll taxes, excise taxes and the like. And most have income taxes withheld from their paychecks but get these payments returned from the government in the form of refunds or credits.</p>
<p>There are also people who make money, have no tax withheld, and owe no tax. Think low-income retirees who are living on Social Security or younger adults who work but make very little.     </p>
<p>But a surprisingly large number of people do work, do have taxes withheld, but never file 1040s. Because we don’t know much about them, TPC treats them as non-payers of income tax even though some do pay through withholding. As a result, our estimate that 43 percent of Americans don’t pay federal income tax is probably high.</p>
<p>A <a href="http://www.ntanet.org/images/stories/pdf/proceedings/09/011.pdf">2005 paper for the <i>National Tax Association Proceedings</i></a> by Jacob Mortenson of the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, James Cilke of the congressional Joint Committee on Taxation, Michael Udell of Ernst &amp; Young, and Jonathon Zytnick of Yale explores the phenomenon.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, their paper uses what are now fairly old data (from 2003) but there is no reason to believe matters have changed very much in the past decade.  </p>
<p>It isn’t easy to learn about these non-filing taxpayers, mostly because the IRS only publishes data about those who do file tax returns. But the authors used information returns such as W-2s and 1099s to build a broad profile.</p>
<p>Not surprisingly, non-filers who had tax withheld earned a limited amount of income. The NTA paper figures an average of only about $20,500 in 2003. And the vast majority of their income was from wages. Keep in mind, though, that this estimate is based on what was reported on those information returns. Some non-filers surely had unreported income as well.</p>
<p>A more recent <a href="http://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-soi/11rescontaxposition.pdf">paper for the IRS publication <i>Statistics of Income</i></a> also found a signficant number of non-filers who had tax withheld. That paper, by Udell and Joshua Lawrence of Ernst &amp; Young and Tiffany Young at Yale, used 2005 information return data. It estimated that non-filers missed out on $3.8 billion in potential refunds of withheld income tax and another $5 billion in refundable credits.</p>
<p>Of course, while many non-filers are owed money by the federal government there are also many who owe taxes, including some who had tax withheld.</p>
<p>It is easy to understand the motivations of those who owe Uncle Sam and don’t file (such a course of action isn’t very smart but it is explainable). It is much harder to figure out why someone who has tax withheld and is likely eligible for refunds or refundable tax credits doesn’t bother. We can all speculate about what is happening here, but it would sure be nice to learn more about these taxpaying non-filers.</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=ZA2mrOIb4TQ:FonMV_LfcPk:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=ZA2mrOIb4TQ:FonMV_LfcPk:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=ZA2mrOIb4TQ:FonMV_LfcPk:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=ZA2mrOIb4TQ:FonMV_LfcPk:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/ZA2mrOIb4TQ" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/03/are-some-americans-paying-federal-income-tax-they-dont-owe/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>6</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/09/03/are-some-americans-paying-federal-income-tax-they-dont-owe/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>IRS Recognizes Same-Sex Marriages, Regardless of Where Couples Live</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/e-qCQfDucAE/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/30/irs-recognizes-same-sex-marriages-regardless-of-where-couples-live/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2013 16:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Roberton Williams</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[About TaxVox]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Individual Income Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marriage Penalty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Payroll taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Same-sex couples]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[State and Local Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[amended return]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[amended tax return]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Defense of Marriage Act]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[DOMA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[federal income tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gay couples]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gay marriage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[IRS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[marriage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[marriage penalty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[payroll tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[same-sex]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[same-sex couples]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5290</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Just two weeks ago, I discussed potential tax issues a same-sex married couple could face if they live in a state that doesn’t recognize their marriage. Yesterday the IRS ruled that, for tax purposes, such couples are married regardless of where they live. That ruling answers the question of what filing status the couple must [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Just two weeks ago, I <a href="http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/15/same-sex-couples-after-doma/">discussed potential tax issues</a> a same-sex married couple could face if they live in a state that doesn’t recognize their marriage. Yesterday <a href="http://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-drop/rr-13-17.pdf">the IRS ruled</a> that, for tax purposes, such couples are married regardless of where they live. That ruling answers the question of what filing status the couple must use but also complicates tax filing for same-sex couples that live in states that prohibit their marriages.</p>
<p>The IRS based its decision on a 1958 ruling that recognized common law marriages established in states that allowed them, even if a couple subsequently moved to a state that did not recognize such unions. Affected couples could continue to file federal tax returns as a married couple, even though their resident states considered them to be single. Notably, yesterday&#8217;s ruling also said that the IRS will not consider registered domestic partnerships, civil unions, and other similar formal relationships to be marriages.</p>
<p>The ruling renders half of the table in my earlier post irrelevant (see new table) but leaves in place the table’s most complicated cells. A same-sex married couple that lives in a state that doesn’t recognize their marriage will have to file a married federal return and two individual state returns. In many states, the latter will require them to create two fictitious individual federal returns, because such returns are the basis for filing their state returns. Tax preparation software will surely handle the complication seamlessly but affected couples will still have to make decisions about which spouse claims their various deductions and non-wage income. And pity the couples that complete their tax returns the old fashioned way using pencil, paper, and a calculator.<br />
<a href="http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/Same-sex-table-w-X.jpg"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-5291" alt="Same-sex table w-X" src="http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/Same-sex-table-w-X.jpg" width="408" height="157" /></a></p>
<p>The IRS ruling allows—but does not require—same-sex couples to amend tax returns filed over the past three years, refiling as married couples. Some couples should not refile: they could incur a dreaded marriage penalty, but they may have to fill out a new return to get the bad news. Going forward, they won’t have any choice—they will have to file married returns.</p>
<p>That decision is further complicated for couples in which one spouse has paid taxes on employer-paid health insurance premiums to cover the other spouse. Until now, those premiums counted as earnings and were subject to both income and payroll taxes. Premiums often totaled thousands of dollars each year and resulted in significantly bigger tax bills. The IRS now says that workers can amend tax returns to exclude that fringe benefit (and others) from taxable income. They can also recover any extra payroll taxes they incurred—as can their employers.</p>
<p>The IRS ruling means that, at least for tax purposes, the marital status of same-sex couples won’t change when they move across state lines. But that doesn’t mean that their lives will be any easier when April 15 rolls around.</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=e-qCQfDucAE:ctEHnLaooVk:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=e-qCQfDucAE:ctEHnLaooVk:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=e-qCQfDucAE:ctEHnLaooVk:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=e-qCQfDucAE:ctEHnLaooVk:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/e-qCQfDucAE" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/30/irs-recognizes-same-sex-marriages-regardless-of-where-couples-live/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>7</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/30/irs-recognizes-same-sex-marriages-regardless-of-where-couples-live/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>And Now for the Movie: Fewer Americans Pay No Federal Income Tax</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/9XPWnaxi3cM/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/29/and-now-for-the-movie-fewer-americans-pay-no-federal-income-tax/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2013 15:51:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Roberton Williams</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[About TaxVox]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Individual Income Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[47 percent]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[47%]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[federal income tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[makers and takers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax expenditures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax preferences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[who pays no federal income tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[who pays no income tax]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5272</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The percentage of Americans who pay no federal income tax is falling, thanks to an improving economy and the expiration of temporary Great Recession-era tax cuts. In 2009, the Tax Policy Center estimated that 47 percent of households paid no federal income tax. This year, just 43 percent will avoid the tax. TPC’s 2009 estimate [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The percentage of Americans who pay no federal income tax is falling, thanks to an improving economy and the expiration of temporary Great Recession-era tax cuts. In 2009, the Tax Policy Center estimated that 47 percent of households paid no federal income tax. This year, just 43 percent will avoid the tax.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.urban.org//UploadedPDF/1001289_who_pays.pdf">TPC’s 2009 estimate</a> went viral during the following tax season and then played a supporting role in last year’s presidential election. Many commentators misinterpreted the estimate as saying that nearly half of all households paid no tax at all when, in fact, nearly everyone pays something. Even if they don’t pay federal income tax, Americans almost all pay Social Security and Medicare payroll taxes, state and local sales taxes, excise taxes, or some other levy.</p>
<p>This new TPC <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nM7orhQIzKM&amp;feature=youtu.be">whiteboard video </a>explains what’s really going on and why the number of people paying no federal income tax is falling.<br />
<iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/nM7orhQIzKM" height="315" width="420" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0"></iframe></p>
<p>The <a href="http://taxpolicycenter.org/taxtopics/No_Tax_Liability_Tables_2.cfm">new TPC estimates</a> project that the fraction of households with no federal income tax liability will continue to fall over the next decade. By 2024, only one-third will pay no income tax.</p>
<p>Of the 43 percent of households that will owe no federal income tax this year, nearly half will be off the rolls because their incomes are too low. The rest won’t pay because preferences wipe out the taxes they would otherwise owe. Many of those preferences, such as the <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/briefing-book/key-elements/family/eitc.cfm">Earned Income Tax Credit</a> and the <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/briefing-book/key-elements/family/ctc.cfm">Child Tax Credit</a>, are social policy run through the tax code. If those provisions were considered spending rather than tax cuts, many more people would be counted among income tax payers. (Indeed, for budgetary purposes, much of the value of those tax credits is considered an outlay.)</p>
<p>Fully <a href="http://taxpolicycenter.org/taxtopics/federal-taxes-households.cfm">two-thirds of households</a> that pay no federal income tax have workers that pay payroll taxes. Most American workers pay more in Social Security and Medicare payroll taxes than income taxes. Just 14 percent of households pay neither income nor payroll tax and two-thirds of them are elderly.</p>
<p>Most of the rest are younger households with no workers and income under $20,000. They pay no income taxes because they have little or no income. The remaining 1 percent mostly benefit from the tax code’s many exclusions, deductions, exemptions, and credits that wipe out the income tax they would otherwise owe.</p>
<p>Even the 14 percent of households that pay neither income nor payroll tax do pay other taxes. Most of us bear some of the burden of the corporate income tax through reduced earnings in our retirement and investment accounts or somewhat lower wages. Anyone who buys gas, tobacco products, alcoholic beverages, or airplane tickets pays federal excise taxes. And it’s nearly impossible to avoid all state and local taxes—the income, sales, and property taxes that support state and local governments.</p>
<p>The notoriety of the 47 percent figure has come largely from a misunderstanding—or less charitably, a misrepresentation—of what that number actually means. Check out <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nM7orhQIzKM&amp;feature=youtu.be">the video</a> and learn the real story about why people pay no income tax and why the number of those who don’t is falling.</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=9XPWnaxi3cM:e8AAQ_IVebk:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=9XPWnaxi3cM:e8AAQ_IVebk:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=9XPWnaxi3cM:e8AAQ_IVebk:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=9XPWnaxi3cM:e8AAQ_IVebk:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/9XPWnaxi3cM" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/29/and-now-for-the-movie-fewer-americans-pay-no-federal-income-tax/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>62</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/29/and-now-for-the-movie-fewer-americans-pay-no-federal-income-tax/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>How Washington Will Use the Coming Budget Wars To Duck Hard Choices</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/UN4tSqAnf9g/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/27/how-washington-will-use-the-coming-budget-wars-to-duck-hard-choices/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2013 19:05:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Howard Gleckman</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Federal Budget & Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2014 budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Affordable Care Act]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Congress]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dave Camp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medicare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sequester]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5266</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Treasury Secretary Jack Lew has notified Congress that the U.S. government will reach the limits of its ability to borrow in mid-October.  Lew’s letter sounds the opening notes of the overture to this fall’s fiscal grand opera. Between October 1 and the end of the calendar year, President Obama and Congress will battle over the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Treasury Secretary Jack Lew has <a href="http://www.treasury.gov/initiatives/Documents/082613%20Debt%20Limit%20Letter%20to%20Congress.pdf">notified Congress</a> that the U.S. government will reach the limits of its ability to borrow in mid-October.  Lew’s letter sounds the opening notes of the overture to this fall’s fiscal grand opera. Between October 1 and the end of the calendar year, President Obama and Congress will battle over the debt limit, fiscal 2014 spending, and a fistful of expiring tax provisions.</p>
<p>A dwindling few see this depressing confluence of fiscal deadlines as an opportunity to reach the long-awaited Grand Bargain. But in reality it is just the opposite, an excuse to avoid the tough choices of tax and entitlement reform. After all, it is easier for Washington to battle over self-made, short-term crises than resolve structural tax and spending challenges.</p>
<p>If you are a Republican, it is easier to demand that the Affordable Care Act be defunded than to back tough, specific cuts to Medicare. If you are Democrat, it is easier to rail against the inequities of the sequester than kill government programs that don’t work. And if you are a politician of either party, it is much easier to embrace the vague concept of tax reform than to cut specific popular <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/publications/url.cfm?ID=412861" target="_blank">tax preferences</a>.</p>
<p>But having raised the profile of the great budget debate, lawmakers can’t just walk away from it. This is especially true for Republicans, who must somehow satisfy their tea party wing. But Democrats have something of the same problem with their left, weakened as that faction is these days.  So they need a distraction from the tough choices. What better diversion than a good headline-generating brawl.  </p>
<p>While a handful of lawmakers seem serious about remaking fiscal policy, most have a different agenda: Saving face without doing much at all.</p>
<p>Thus between now and New Year’s Day Washington will focus on trivia. Will the debt limit be extended for six months or a year? Will Congress fund 2014 agency budgets at sequester levels, Obama’s proposed levels, or something in the middle—an argument likely to center on about 1 percent of total federal spending?</p>
<p>House Ways &amp; Means Committee Chairman Dave Camp (R-MI) says that in October&#8211;in the midst of all that noise—he’ll propose his version of tax reform. In a healthy political environment, Camp’s plan would kick off a welcome debate over tax reform. But in the current dysfunctional atmosphere, it is likely to get lost in the cacophony. This will be too bad. But for many in Washington, replacing serious debate with loud short-term squabbles over phony fiscal crises is exactly the idea.      </p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=UN4tSqAnf9g:PDctEK7VtwM:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=UN4tSqAnf9g:PDctEK7VtwM:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=UN4tSqAnf9g:PDctEK7VtwM:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=UN4tSqAnf9g:PDctEK7VtwM:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/UN4tSqAnf9g" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/27/how-washington-will-use-the-coming-budget-wars-to-duck-hard-choices/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/27/how-washington-will-use-the-coming-budget-wars-to-duck-hard-choices/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Honey, I Shrunk the AMT (But It’s Not Gone)</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/CU3mpBHLyXk/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/26/honey-i-shrunk-the-amt-but-its-not-gone/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2013 22:22:24 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Roberton Williams</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Alternative Minimum Tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[American Tax Relief Act of 2012]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Individual Income Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AMT patch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ATRA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[federal income tax]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5259</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The tax act Congress passed early on New Year’s Day permanently patched the alternative minimum tax (AMT), sparing tens of millions of Americans from the additional levy. But it won’t protect everyone. The AMT will continue to raise the taxes of a few million taxpayers each year, often in seemingly capricious ways. And more and [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">The tax act Congress passed early on New Year’s Day permanently patched the <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/briefing-book/key-elements/amt/index.cfm">alternative minimum tax</a> (AMT), sparing tens of millions of Americans from the additional levy. But it won’t protect everyone. The AMT will continue to raise the taxes of a few million taxpayers each year, often in seemingly capricious ways. And more and more Americans will owe AMT in future years.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;"><a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/numbers/displayatab.cfm?template=simulation&amp;SimID=476">New estimates from the Tax Policy Center</a> project that 3.9 million taxpayers will pay an average of about $6,600 in AMT for 2013, increasing their average effective tax rate by 1.7 percentage points. And the percentage of taxpayers who owe the additional tax—4.2 percent this year—will rise steadily over the next decade before leveling off at about 5.5 percent. That means more than 6 million taxpayers will pay AMT in 2023.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">As in the past, married couples, families with more children, and people living in high-tax states will be most likely to incur the added tax. Taxpayers with income between $200,000 and $1 million will be most affected: about one-third of them will owe AMT.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">For nearly a decade, Congress temporarily adjusted the AMT exemption every year or two to keep the tax from hitting millions of unsuspecting taxpayers. Those fixes often came late in the year, creating a lot of uncertainty for taxpayers. The <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/UploadedPDF/412730-Tax-Provisions-in-ATRA.pdf">American Taxpayer Relief Act of 2012</a> (ATRA) permanently indexed the exemption and other AMT parameters.   Congress might have gone the extra mile and eliminated the AMT entirely, but that would have cost more than $350 billion in lost revenue over the next decade.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">So the AMT lives on, complicating the tax returns of more Americans every year. For many, it will come as a nasty surprise: new AMT taxpayers often learn about the bonus tax only when a letter from the IRS tells them they owe extra tax plus interest and possibly penalties.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">And, as bad tax policy as it is, the AMT is unlikely to go away—not unless comprehensive tax reform finally rids us of this tax code abomination.</span></p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=CU3mpBHLyXk:F95sFtl_sCg:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=CU3mpBHLyXk:F95sFtl_sCg:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=CU3mpBHLyXk:F95sFtl_sCg:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=CU3mpBHLyXk:F95sFtl_sCg:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/CU3mpBHLyXk" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/26/honey-i-shrunk-the-amt-but-its-not-gone/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>6</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/26/honey-i-shrunk-the-amt-but-its-not-gone/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>The Center for American Progress Rethinks Retirement Savings</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/IULWdjX1n3M/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/22/the-center-for-american-progress-rethinks-retirement-savings/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2013 20:53:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Howard Gleckman</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Retirement Plans]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The US Tax System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[401(k)s]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Center for American Progress]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[David Madland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[defined benefit pensions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[retirement savings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rowland Davis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SAFE plan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Policy Center]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5255</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Kudos to Rowland Davis and David Madland at the Center for American Progress for rethinking retirement savings. In a paper with the rather understated title “American Retirement Savings Could Be Much Better,” the authors attempt to stitch together the best of defined contribution plans and defined benefit pensions. Their preferred vehicle is what’s known as a [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Kudos to Rowland Davis and David Madland at the Center for American Progress for rethinking retirement savings. In a <a href="http://www.americanprogress.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/SAFEreport.pdf">paper</a> with the rather understated title “American Retirement Savings Could Be Much Better,” the authors attempt to stitch together the best of defined contribution plans and defined benefit pensions.</p>
<p>Their preferred vehicle is what’s known as a collective defined contribution plan (they call their version the Secure, Accessible, Flexible, and Efficient (SAFE) plan).</p>
<p>Today, workers in 401(k) plans bear full investment risk and often struggle with how to allocate their retirement savings and what to do with their assets when they change jobs or retire. With SAFE, those risks would be mitigated. <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/publications/url.cfm?ID=1001597">Enrollment would be automatic</a>, savings fully portable, and investment funds pooled and professionally managed. Accounts would be automatically annuitized as in traditional DB plans.</p>
<p>Investment pools would be run by private non-profits but professionally managed. Employers could contribute to workers’ accounts but would have no fiduciary obligations since they’d play no role in managing the assets.</p>
<p>The model attempts to spread risk among workers of all ages and retirees. It also would use a financial tool called a collar aimed at smoothing investment returns. The authors model a plan that aims to credit fund participants with annual returns that range from zero to 8 percent. In years where investment profits top 8 percent, the excess would be held in a notional reserve fund. In years when returns fall below zero those reserves would cover any losses.    </p>
<p>Sensibly, the authors do not promise riskless returns. But they say their model would keep both risks and costs relatively low. They estimate that, by doing so, workers saving through such a model would be more than twice as likely to maintain their standard of living in retirement as workers making identical contributions to a traditional 401(k) plan.</p>
<p>Still, there are plenty of questions about the proposal. To name just three: The estimated returns to these plans seem very optimistic, the transition quite complex and potentially costly, and the government’s role in organizing or reinsuring plans is just not clear.    </p>
<p>One attractive element of the plan is that it builds on existing savings vehicles and does not propose to add any new tax-advantaged schemes to the dozens that already exist. The last thing we need is another savings subsidy.</p>
<p>Many large employers already offer automatic enrollment, life cycle investment funds, and annuitization aimed at improving (401)k plans—often making them look a bit like pensions. But this happens in an ad hoc way and without the benefits of reduced costs and risks that come, at least in theory, with a pooled plan design such as SAFE.</p>
<p>This idea has a lot going for it. At the very least it could jump-start a badly-needed debate over how to build a better retirement system.</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=IULWdjX1n3M:WoO5nFptudU:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=IULWdjX1n3M:WoO5nFptudU:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=IULWdjX1n3M:WoO5nFptudU:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=IULWdjX1n3M:WoO5nFptudU:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/IULWdjX1n3M" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/22/the-center-for-american-progress-rethinks-retirement-savings/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>15</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/22/the-center-for-american-progress-rethinks-retirement-savings/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Why Legal Marijuana is a Good Argument for Tax Reform</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/PcwvlDMKMLg/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/20/why-legal-marijuana-is-a-good-argument-for-tax-reform/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2013 19:31:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Howard Gleckman</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[State & Local Issues]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[State and Local Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Proposals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dave Camp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[marijuana]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[marijuana taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax expenditures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Washington State]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5252</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[“Marijuana Industry Eager to Pay Taxes &#8211; and Cash in on Deductions” That was the headline for a story written by Rob Hotakainen of McClatchy Newspapers the other day. In less than a dozen words, it describes much of what’s wrong with the federal tax system.  And in an odd way it helps explain why [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>“Marijuana Industry Eager to Pay Taxes &#8211; and Cash in on Deductions”</p>
<p>That was the <a href="http://www.kansascity.com/2013/08/18/4415508/marijuana-industry-eager-to-pay.html">headline for a story</a> written by Rob Hotakainen of McClatchy Newspapers the other day. In less than a dozen words, it describes much of what’s wrong with the federal tax system.  And in an odd way it helps explain why tax reform is such a good idea.</p>
<p>State-legal marijuana producers and retailers are seeking to take advantage of deductions they are now denied under their ambiguous legal status. And, <a href="http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/06/06/let-legal-marijuana-dispensaries-deduct-their-business-expenses/">as I’ve written in the past</a>, they probably should be allowed to do so. But some may want to get into the tax system just so they can harvest the many generous deductions it offers.</p>
<p>That pungent odor you smell isn’t Blue Skunk Special. It may be the sweet scent of a tax shelter wafting through the door.</p>
<p>First, let’s parse what’s going on. Several states have recently made marijuana legal. But weed remains illegal under federal law. Thus, while growers and sellers must pay federal income tax on their profits, they are explicitly barred under the Revenue Code from claiming deductions or credits.  Buyers don’t pay federal excise taxes as they might if they purchased, say, beer or cigarettes.</p>
<p>To be clear, the state-legal marijuana industry Rob wrote about doesn’t want to pay more taxes itself. Indeed, by gaining access to deductions, it would pay less. Buyers, on the other hand, would pay a new tax. Backers estimate a $50-per-once retail-level levy would generate about $20 billion a year.  </p>
<p>This is enough to give at least a few members of Congress the revenue munchies. And a couple of bills have been introduced to legalize, regulate, and tax sales of grass. <a href="http://blumenauer.house.gov/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=2213%3Asmall-business-tax-equity-act-faq&amp;catid=24%3Alegislation&amp;Itemid=1">One would create a national system</a>. The other would allow states to tax marijuana—and grant deductions. Washington State wants to impose a 25 percent Value-Added-type tax on producers, processors, and retailers.</p>
<p>It would be interesting to figure out whether such a levy turns out to exceed an income tax without deductions. But either way, much of that tax would be passed on to buyers in the form of, um, higher prices. How much would depend on the willingness of buyers to pay more for legal taxable weed rather than lower-cost but riskier illegal dope. </p>
<p>The new tax liability is all about the buyers, while growers and sellers have their eye on the deductions that come along with being in the tax system. They may be dope sellers, but they are still business people who want to maximize after-tax returns.</p>
<p>For instance, retailers could deduct costs such as rent, legal fees, and wages. And, like other small businesses, they might write off automobiles and office equipment. Growers could deduct the cost of farm equipment and the like.</p>
<p>This does get complicated. The current uncertain system discourages legal, regulated sales and encourages a black market, even in states where marijuana is legal. After all, paying federal tax without the benefit of deductions is a huge disincentive to reporting marijuana income. On the other hand, access to deductions may encourage the sort of gaming that infects today’s tax system.</p>
<p>While I’m sure this isn’t what the state-legal marijuana industry had in mind, the curious situation in which it finds itself may be yet another argument for trading off all those tax preferences for lower rates. After all, in a system without deductions and credits the marijuana industry would be treated no differently than any other business.</p>
<p>The legal dope industry is probably not the tax reform poster child House Ways &amp; Means Committee Chairman Dave Camp (R-MI) is looking for. Still, its plight is an instructive story.</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=PcwvlDMKMLg:oWpCQTBn7WE:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=PcwvlDMKMLg:oWpCQTBn7WE:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=PcwvlDMKMLg:oWpCQTBn7WE:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=PcwvlDMKMLg:oWpCQTBn7WE:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/PcwvlDMKMLg" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/20/why-legal-marijuana-is-a-good-argument-for-tax-reform/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/20/why-legal-marijuana-is-a-good-argument-for-tax-reform/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Same-Sex Couples after DOMA</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/nmWmZIPBwjM/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/15/same-sex-couples-after-doma/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2013 19:24:58 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Roberton Williams</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Individual Income Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marriage Penalty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[State and Local Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Defense of Marriage Act]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[DOMA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[federal income taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gay marriage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[marriage bonus]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[marriage penalty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[same-sex]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[same-sex couples]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[same-sex marriage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme Court]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5247</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[It’s been less than two months since the Supreme Court ruled part of the Defense of Marriage Act (DOMA) unconstitutional and the fallout has only begun to settle. Nowhere is there more uncertainty about the effects of the ruling than regarding federal taxes. The court struck down Section 3 of DOMA, which denied federal recognition [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It’s been less than two months since the <a href="http://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/12pdf/12-307_6j37.pdf">Supreme Court ruled</a> part of the <a href="http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/PLAW-104publ199/pdf/PLAW-104publ199.pdf">Defense of Marriage Act (DOMA)</a> unconstitutional and the fallout has only begun to settle. Nowhere is there more uncertainty about the effects of the ruling than regarding federal taxes.</p>
<p>The court struck down Section 3 of DOMA, which denied federal recognition of same-sex marriages. It left in place Section 2, which allows states to refuse to recognize same-sex marriages performed in other states. That means that if a same-sex couple legally married in a state that allows gay marriage subsequently moves to a state that doesn’t, their marriage ceases to exist where they reside.</p>
<p>What does that mean for the couple’s federal taxes? While they live in a state allowing same-sex marriage, the couple must file federal tax returns as a married couple. What happens when they move to a state that denies their marriage is <a href="http://www.irs.gov/uac/Answers-to-Frequently-Asked-Questions-for-Same-Sex-Couples">not yet clear</a>. That depends on whether the IRS decides to define marriage based on the couple’s residence or their “place of ceremony,” the state where they were married.</p>
<p>Historically, the IRS has followed a residency rule in determining marital status. If the state where you live says you’re married, you must file your federal tax return as married (although that obviously didn’t apply for same-sex couples under DOMA). If your state says you aren’t married, you must file as unmarried.</p>
<p>Under a residency rule, a married same-sex couple living in Maryland&#8211;which recognizes their marriage—must file their federal tax returns as married, either jointly or separately. If they move across the Potomac into Virginia—which constitutionally bars recognition of all same-sex marriages—they must switch to filing single or head of household returns. Unless Congress or the courts undo DOMA’s Section 2, that situation will prevail.</p>
<p>If the IRS chooses instead to switch to a place of ceremony approach, same-sex couples who marry in one of the 13 states or the District of Columbia that allow such marriage will have to file their federal tax returns as married, regardless of where they subsequently live. State law will determine their state tax filing status but they would file the same federal returns regardless of where they live.</p>
<p>So far, the <a href="http://www.irs.gov/uac/Answers-to-Frequently-Asked-Questions-for-Same-Sex-Couples">IRS has given no indication </a>of which approach it will follow. However, other parts of the federal government have chosen the place-of-ceremony approach. In fact, the Defense Department has gone so far as to grant up to ten days leave for same-sex couples living in states that bar their marriage so they can travel to wed in states that will let them marry.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">So where does that leave same-sex couples? It depends (see table). <img class="size-full wp-image-5244 aligncenter" alt="Same-Sex couples and IRS-table-540x211" src="http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/Same-Sex-couples-and-IRS-table-540x211.png" width="540" height="211" /></p>
<p>A married same-sex couple living in a state that recognizes their marriage will no longer have to file tax returns as married with the state and single with the feds. Depending on the couple’s financial circumstances, filing a joint federal return may incur a marriage penalty or reap a marriage bonus, neither of which could occur under DOMA. The couple will also have to decide whether it makes sense to amend their federal tax returns for the past three years to claim any tax savings they might get filing jointly. The IRS has said that couples may—but don’t have to—amend those returns. Presumably those getting marriage bonuses would generally opt to refile, while those incurring penalties would not.</p>
<p>The situation facing a same-sex couple that wed in a state that allows same-sex marriage but now lives in a state that does not depends on how the IRS determines their marital status. If the IRS continues to use a residence approach, they, like all other same-sex couples in states that don’t allow same-sex marriage, will file both state and federal tax returns as individuals.</p>
<p>If the IRS instead moves to a place-of-ceremony approach, the couple will have to file federal tax returns as a married couple and state tax returns as individuals. Since state returns often start with values taken from federal returns, that means they will bear the additional burden of having to prepare individual federal returns and not file them.</p>
<p>It’s not obvious what the IRS should do. Marriage has traditionally fallen in the province of state law, which suggests that a residence rule should apply. But imposing a change in filing status on couples simply because they move across state lines makes little sense from either a tax or social policy perspective.</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=nmWmZIPBwjM:ND92Y51J_Ow:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=nmWmZIPBwjM:ND92Y51J_Ow:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=nmWmZIPBwjM:ND92Y51J_Ow:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=nmWmZIPBwjM:ND92Y51J_Ow:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/nmWmZIPBwjM" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/15/same-sex-couples-after-doma/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>10</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/15/same-sex-couples-after-doma/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Paying for Corporate Tax Rate Cuts is Hard</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/NHvGgHy3QMw/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/13/paying-for-corporate-tax-rate-cuts-is-hard/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2013 21:03:30 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Roberton Williams</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Corporate Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[accelerated depreciation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[base broadening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[corporate income tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[corporate tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[corporate tax cut]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[deferral]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[House budget resolution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax expenditures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax reform]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5233</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Covering the revenue loss from deep individual income tax rate cuts while maintaining the income tax’s current progressivity is difficult, as Howard Gleckman explained here last week. It turns out that paying for corporate tax rate cuts is even harder. And new Tax Policy Center estimates show that lowering corporate tax rates without paying for [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Covering the revenue loss from deep individual income tax rate cuts while maintaining the income tax’s current progressivity is difficult, as Howard Gleckman <a href="http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/08/beware-of-tax-reform-that-promises-deep-rate-cuts/">explained here</a> last week. It turns out that paying for corporate tax rate cuts is even harder. And new Tax Policy Center estimates show that lowering corporate tax rates without paying for lost revenue would be highly regressive.</p>
<p>Calls for reducing the top corporate tax rate from the current 35 percent have come from a wide array of sources, ranging from the president to members of Congress on both sides of the aisle to the business community and many economists. Our top rate is higher than that of any other developed country. That discourages investment in the U.S., and encourages income-shifting to avoid tax. Cutting our corporate tax rate makes economic sense.</p>
<p>But, as is the case with the individual income tax, proposals to reduce corporate taxes haven’t included specific provisions to replace the lost revenue.</p>
<p>That cost isn’t small: The Joint Committee on Taxation <a href="http://democrats.waysandmeans.house.gov/sites/democrats.waysandmeans.house.gov/files/Scan001.pdf">recently estimated</a> that cutting the rate to 25 percent—and eliminating the corporate alternative minimum tax—would reduce revenue by $1.3 trillion over the next decade. Proponents of rate cuts generally imply that they would cover the lost revenue by paring back or eliminating corporate tax expenditures. The problem with that is there aren’t enough of the latter.</p>
<p>On paper, the sum of Treasury estimates of corporate tax expenditures appears to be big enough that eliminating them could pay for the rate cut. But a closer look suggests otherwise.</p>
<p>The two biggest tax expenditures are the deferral of foreign-source income of U.S. controlled foreign corporations and accelerated depreciation for machinery and equipment. But eliminating deferral would raise much less after the rate cut than the tax expenditure estimate, simply because deferral saves much less tax with lower rates. And in any case, Congress is unlikely to cut back on deferral: this year’s <a href="http://budget.house.gov/uploadedfiles/fy14budget.pdf">House budget resolution </a>went the other way, proposing a territorial tax that would exempt most foreign-source income.</p>
<p>Eliminating accelerated depreciation is also unlikely. Recent administration budgets have proposed making depreciation more generous, not less. And eliminating accelerated depreciation to pay for rate cuts for all corporations would raise the effective tax rate on new investments in U.S. manufacturing.</p>
<p>Take those big preferences off the table and the revenue potential of base-broadening shrinks dramatically.</p>
<p>If we don’t pay for a corporate rate cut by broadening the tax base, whom would the cut benefit (beyond any potential boost to the economy)? Even though corporations write the checks, the tax is ultimately borne by people—investors, workers, or consumers. While economists disagree about how the burdens are distributed, our best reading of the evidence is that 20 percent of the tax falls on workers and the rest hits owners of capital. Most of the tax falls on high-income households because they own most of the nation’s capital.</p>
<p>As a result, reducing the corporate tax rate by itself would be highly regressive, as TPC’s <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/numbers/displayatab.cfm?Docid=3963">new tables</a> show. More than two-thirds of the tax savings would go to the top 20 percent of households and slightly more than half of that to the top 1 percent—households making more than about $2.1 million in 2015. Their taxes would drop an average of more than $35,000 that year, boosting their after-tax income by 2.6 percent. In contrast, people in the middle 20 percent—making an average of about $66,000—would pay an average of $300 less in corporate income tax, ticking their after-tax income up just 0.5 percent.</p>
<p>If it were possible and politically feasible, paying for the rate cut by paring back corporate tax expenditures would undo some or all of that regressivity. Just as lowering corporate taxes disproportionately benefits high-income taxpayers, raising the tax disproportionately harms them.</p>
<p>Whether Congress can find enough tax increases to offset the revenue lost from cutting corporate tax rates will determine the answers to two important questions: whether corporate tax reform will be revenue neutral and whether changes will affect the progressivity of the tax.</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=NHvGgHy3QMw:rT54mpii46I:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=NHvGgHy3QMw:rT54mpii46I:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=NHvGgHy3QMw:rT54mpii46I:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=NHvGgHy3QMw:rT54mpii46I:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/NHvGgHy3QMw" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/13/paying-for-corporate-tax-rate-cuts-is-hard/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>7</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/13/paying-for-corporate-tax-rate-cuts-is-hard/</feedburner:origLink></item>
		<item>
		<title>Beware of Tax Reform That Promises Deep Rate Cuts</title>
		<link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~3/y51xOjaeIpA/</link>
		<comments>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/08/beware-of-tax-reform-that-promises-deep-rate-cuts/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2013 18:22:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Howard Gleckman</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Individual Income Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Expenditures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Proposals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The US Tax System]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Types of Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Capital Gains Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[expanded cash income]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Joint Committee on Taxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax expenditures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Policy Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax preferences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax rates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax reform]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="0">http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/?p=5227</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Two new studies show just how hard a time Congress will have trying to slash tax rates without adding trillions of dollars to the budget deficit and producing a massive tax windfall for the highest-income American households. Last week, the congressional Joint Committee on Taxation estimated that a tax plan that cuts individual rates to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Two new studies show just how hard a time Congress will have trying to slash tax rates without adding trillions of dollars to the budget deficit and producing a massive tax windfall for the highest-income American households.</p>
<p>Last week, the congressional Joint Committee on Taxation <a href="http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/06/a-summer-update-on-tax-reform/">estimated</a> that a tax plan that cuts individual rates to 10 percent and 25 percent and repeals the Alternative Minimum Tax would add almost $3.8 trillion to the budget deficit over 10 years. A plan to cut the corporate rate to 25 percent and repeal the corporate AMT would add another $1.3 trillion to the deficit.</p>
<p>Now the Tax Policy Center <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/numbers/displayatab.cfm?Docid=3961&amp;DocTypeID=2">has looked at</a> how the individual design would affect households in various income groups. Not only would such a rewrite dig a deep fiscal hole but it would also be extremely regressive. In 2015, it would cut taxes for those households in the lowest 20 percent of income (who will make roughly $25,000 or less) by an average of $3. By contrast, those in the top 1 percent (who will make an average of $2.1 million) would get an average tax cut of almost $145,000, a 10 percent boost in their after-tax income.</p>
<p>Middle income households (who will make an average of about $66,000) would get about $700, boosting their after-tax income by about 1.2 percent.</p>
<p>To put it another way, the top 20 percent of households would get nearly four-fifths of the tax cut. The top 1 percent would get more than half.</p>
<p>The TPC estimates use our new expanded cash income measure and thus are somewhat different than earlier estimates of similar proposals.</p>
<p>Keep in mind: No one has proposed a plan exactly like this. While many top congressional Republicans favor a similar rate strucure, they also say they’d pay for these rate reductions by curtailing (yet-unspecified) tax preferences.</p>
<p>The JCT revenue estimate and the TPC distributional analysis describe the challenges of enacting such a rate-cutting plan in a way that collects the same amount of money and maintains the same distribution as current revenue law.</p>
<p>Can this problem be solved?  Honestly, with rates this low, probably not. True, Congress could generate the $3.8 trillion in revenue it needs by slashing tax preferences. But since tax expenditures amount to about $1.4 trillion-a-year, popular preferences would have to be cut to the bone to fund a $3.8 trillion tax cut. We’re not talking about loopholes anymore.</p>
<p>Finding this much money would be especially hard since eliminating deductions and exclusions generates less revenue at lower rates (The unforgiving math of tax reform: When the top rate is 39.6 percent, eliminating a deduction yields 39.6 cents on the dollar. If the top rate is 25 percent, eliminating the same deduction yields just 25 cents).</p>
<p>But if Congress aims to maintain the current distribution of tax burdens, finding $3.8 trillion solves only half the problem.</p>
<p>Trouble is, many tax breaks benefit low- and middle-income households, not the rich who’d be big winners from the rate cuts. For instance, the biggest beneficiaries of popular tax preferences such as the mortgage deduction and the exclusion of retirement savings and employer-provided health insurance are middle-and upper-middle income households, not the very rich.</p>
<p>To take just one example, TPC <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/UploadedPDF/412871-measuring-income.pdf">estimates</a> employer-paid health benefits represent about 10 percent of income for middle-income households. Yet they represent only 0.6 percent for those in the Top 1 percent.</p>
<p>There is really only one place Congress can go to significantly trim tax preferences for the highest-income households. And that is capital gains, dividends, and other investment income.</p>
<p>The lesson from these two studies is not new, but it bears repeating:  Cutting tax rates is a great idea in theory, but it is very tough to pull off.</p>
<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=y51xOjaeIpA:5nG5yrSI8PE:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=y51xOjaeIpA:5nG5yrSI8PE:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"></img></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?a=y51xOjaeIpA:5nG5yrSI8PE:WeURFIJcaAU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed?i=y51xOjaeIpA:5nG5yrSI8PE:WeURFIJcaAU" border="0"></img></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/taxpolicycenter/blogfeed/~4/y51xOjaeIpA" height="1" width="1"/>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/08/beware-of-tax-reform-that-promises-deep-rate-cuts/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>6</slash:comments>
		<feedburner:origLink>http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/2013/08/08/beware-of-tax-reform-that-promises-deep-rate-cuts/</feedburner:origLink></item>
	</channel>
</rss><!-- Dynamic page generated in 1.060 seconds. --><!-- Cached page generated by WP-Super-Cache on 2013-10-17 13:31:26 -->
